In the year 1815,
the English colonial official Thomas
Stamford Raffles would travel across the
island of Java in what is today
Indonesia.
At this time, the world was torn by war.
In Europe, the Napoleonic Wars were
raging, and the Earth's oceans had
become just another battlefront.
The lush tropical island of Java had
been until recently a Dutch colony, but
the Netherlands had been conquered by
Napoleon in his advance across Europe.
And so the Dutch colonies had fallen
under the control of the French.
Now the British desired to take Java for
themselves and strike a blow at
Napoleon's overseas empire.
In 1811, British Marines launched an
invasion of Java, landing among its
coral reefs and sky blue oceans,
clambering through its shady mangrove
forests and up its beaches of black
volcanic sand, climbing the steep cliffs
in the shadow of its towering volcanoes.
From there they overwhelmed the
inexperienced Dutch defenders and took
the island for the British Empire.
With them came the Englishman Thomas
Stamford Raffles who later wrote about
these events.
Holland had ceased to be an independent
nation and in the year 1811 the French
flag was hoisted over Java. But on the
17th of September of the same year, a
capitulation was entered into by which
all the dependencies fell into the hands
of Great Britain.
Raffles was a lifelong sailor and had
actually been born at sea on a ship
commanded by his father off the coast of
Jamaica. He became a clerk in the
British East India Company at the age of
14 and from there became a true company
man.
He had spent the best part of the last
decade furthering the interests of
British colonialism in East Asia and had
even become fluent in the language of
Malay.
When Java was captured by the British,
partly as a result of his skill at
languages, Raffles was granted the
position of left tenant governor.
At the age of just 30, Raffles found
himself in charge of an island a
thousand kilometers across, home to more
than 6 million people.
Raffles was fascinated by Java.
He remarked on its dramatic landscape of
soaring volcanoes and steamy
rainforests,
its fertile rice terraces and remarkable
culture, as he wrote home to King George
III.
The gracious permission which I have
received affords me an opportunity of
interesting your royal highness in favor
of the amiiable and ingenious people
whose country they describe. A chain of
very high mountains runs along the whole
length of Java. Even in July and August,
the atmosphere is refreshed by
occasional showers and the landscape is
at all times of the year covered with
the brightest green.
But most of all, he was fascinated by
Java's antiquities.
Everywhere among its forests and shaded
rice terraces could be seen the remains
of the countless temples, palaces, and
even whole ancient cities left in ruins.
A few years later, around 1815, he
embarked on a journey around the island
with the aim of surveying these ruins
and writing a book.
Although by then Java was an
overwhelmingly Muslim land, Raffles
found everywhere the remains of an older
culture hiding just beneath the surface.
As he writes in his work, the history of
Java,
the Muhammadan religion, as it present
exists on Java, seems only to have
penetrated the surface and to have taken
but little root in the heart of Javans.
But the antiquities of Java consist of
ruins of edififices and in particular of
temples sacred to the former worship.
Images of deities found within them and
scattered throughout the country, either
sculpted in stone or cast in metal.
inscriptions on stone and copper in
ancient characters and ancient coins.
Raffles was fascinated by these remains
which seemed to confirm stories he had
heard. Stories of a great empire that
had risen up on that island. A thriving
combination of Hinduism and Buddhism
that had flourished for centuries,
spread its influence across the sea to
countless other islands in the
Indonesian archipelago and built what
may have been one of the largest empires
in Southeast Asia.
This was the empire of Maja Pahit.
The numerous and interesting remains of
former art and grandeur which exist in
the ruins of temples and other
edififices. The abundant treasures of
sculpture and statuary either lay
entirely buried under rubbish or were
but partially examined. Nothing
therefore of the ancient history of the
people of their institutions prior to
the introduction of Muhammadanism of
their magnificence and power could be
accurately known or fully relied on. The
grandeur of their ancestors sounds like
a fable and it is only when it can be
traced in monuments which cannot be
falsified that we are led to give credit
to their traditions concerning it.
Raffles became convinced that he could
find the remnants of the civilization of
Majapahit and so he traveled the length
and breadth of the island and visited
every ruined site he could along the
way.
He stopped at the ancient cities of
Kadiri and Singasari and found there the
crumbling remains of city walls, palaces
and carved statues of the Buddha
alongside Hindu gods.
But when he got to the valley of the
Brontis River in East Java, the locals
advised him not to go near the ruins.
They told him that a terrible curse
still lingered over those crumbling
stones.
The natives had a superstition that the
site of this ancient capital cannot be
visited without some misfortune
attaching to the party who undertake the
visit. Those whom I had with some
difficulty induced to accompany me to
the spot did not fail to assure me that
I should lose my government within the
year.
Finally, Raffles visited the great
capital of Majapahit, which his guides
told him lay buried near the town of
Trrowan.
At Trrowan, Raffles hoped to find a
magnificent ruined city, testifying to
the former greatness of this power.
But when he arrived, he would be
disappointed.
He would find little more than a scatter
of broken brick work and assorted
sculpture littering the landscape,
buried in volcanic ash and shaded
beneath the towering teak trees.
A village adjacent is called Trulan or
the light of the moon. The ruins of the
palace and several gateways of burnt
brick are to be seen, but the whole
country for many miles is thickly
covered with a stately teak forest which
appears to have been the growth of ages
so that it is difficult to trace the
outline of this former capital. Ruins of
temples mostly executed in brick are
scattered about the country for many
miles and attest to the extent and
grandeur of this pride of Java. The
temples are beautifully decorated with
representations of flowers and other
peculiar ornaments which it would be
difficult to describe.
In fact, the local people turned out to
be right and perhaps Raffles should have
listened to their warnings.
Raffles would only govern the island of
Java for another year.
The Napoleonic Wars soon came to an end
and the British returned the colony to
the now independent Dutch, relieving
raffles of his post.
And he would go on to suffer more
misfortune in the years that followed.
Just 10 years later, he would have a
stroke likely caused by an underlying
condition in the blood vessels of his
brain.
This stroke would kill him the day
before his 45th birthday.
As Raffles wandered about those ruins of
crumbling red brick at the sight of the
ancient city of Majapahit, he had no
idea that his fate was already sealed by
the birth defect lurking in his head.
But perhaps that day he thought about
life and death as he walked beneath the
shade of that teak forest and listened
to the calling of coels and minor birds
high in the trees.
Perhaps he thought about the rise and
fall of empires and the changing
fortunes of the world. Perhaps he
wondered how such a power had risen up
on the island of Java and left such a
mark on the memories and imaginations of
that land's people. Perhaps he asked
himself how its people had constructed
these temples and palaces, these walls
and reservoirs,
carved such beautiful and haunting
monuments, and then fallen all at once
into ruin.
My name's Paul Cooper and you're
listening to the fall of civilizations
podcast. Each episode I look at a
civilization of the past that rose to
glory and then collapsed into the ashes
of history.
I want to ask what did they have in
common? What led to their fall? and what
did it feel like to be a person alive at
the time who witnessed the end of their
world.
In this episode, I want to tell the
story of the Majapahit Empire of
medieval Indonesia.
I want to show how this empire of the
islands grew up on the volcanic land of
Java and how it beat the odds to survive
in a world of medieval superpowers.
I want to show how Majapahit expanded
its influence and dominion to other
lands over the seas and undertook
voyages that have few precedents in
history. And I want to show what
happened to bring this Empire of the
Islands finally crashing down.
The surface of planet Earth is a thin
crust of solid rock which sits over the
softer and much hotter mantle beneath
it.
This crust can be as much as 80 km thick
in places and as thin as 10 km in others
and it is divided into seven major
tectonic plates.
The largest of these is the Pacific
plate.
It is a vast sheet of solid rock more
than 100 million square km in size that
makes up much of the floor of the
Pacific Ocean and which alone accounts
for about a fifth of Earth's total
surface.
The Pacific plate is made up almost
entirely of oceanic crust which is
different to the continental crust that
we all live on. Oceanic crust is
typically much thinner but made of
denser bassalt rock.
For this reason, whenever it impacts
with other tectonic plates, the Pacific
plate is pushed downwards into the
Earth's upper mantle, creating a zone of
subduction. And these subduction zones
are renowned for their violent volcanic
activity.
Due to its immense size and density, the
Pacific plate has the most subduction
zones of any tectonic plate. And as a
result, its borders are the most
volcanically active areas on Earth.
This ring of raging volcanoes stretches
in a vast horseshoe shape for more than
40,000 km or about the circumference of
the earth from the southern tip of South
America all around the western shore of
the Americas and then through the sea
down the eastern coast of Asia.
To geologists, it is called the
CircumPacific Belt, but in popular
usage, it has come to be known by
another name, the Pacific Ring of Fire.
The 19th century English geologist
George P. Scro was one of the first to
describe this far-ranging phenomenon.
A striking and constant delineation of
volcanic spiracles is displayed in the
numerous archipelos which bordered the
eastern coast of Asia. Beginning from
the peninsula of Kamchatka, Japan, the
Luchu, Philippines and Malocas form a
scarcely interrupted linear series of
volcanic islands amongst which many
contain vents in habitual activity and
bearing marks of recent and extremely
violent eruptions.
The Pacific Ring of Fire is home to 3/4
of all the world's volcanoes and 90% of
the earthquakes on Earth take place
along this line.
The Ring of Fire has given us some of
the world's most iconic peaks, including
the elegant cone of Mount Fuji in Japan
and the violently explosive Mount St.
Helens in the United States as well as
the volcanoes of Mount Tambora and
Krakatoa whose 1815 and 1883 eruptions
were among the largest in recorded
history
as it is dragged down into the depths of
the planet. The subducting Pacific plate
has also created some of the lowest
places on the Earth's surface, giving
rise to a series of dramatic oceanic
trenches.
The deepest of these, known as the
Marana Trench, reaches a sea depth of 11
km, deeper than Mount Everest is tall.
And in the areas where the ring of fire
passes through open ocean, it has also
created a huge number of volcanic
islands.
As volcanoes erupt under the sea, magma
spews out of the planet's mantle and
cools on contact with cold seaater into
solid rock.
Over time, whole islands form around
these volcanoes.
And on these islands, the lives and
deaths and dramas and tragedies of
millions of human lives have played out
throughout history.
Perhaps the region where the Pacific
Ring of Fire has had the most effect in
sculpting the landscape is in the area
of what is today Malaysia and Indonesia.
Here the Ring of Fire has lifted
thousands of islands large and small
from the sea. And this archipelago has
come to be known by a name that in old
Javanese meant simply the outer lands.
This name is Nusan Tara.
The archipelago today called Nusantara
lies across an area of ocean wider than
the continental United States and laid
over a map of Europe would stretch from
France as far east as northern India.
The archipelago is today home to more
than 700 languages, six major religions,
and more than 300 ethnicities.
And since modern humans first arrived on
these islands, they have given rise to a
huge variety of different peoples.
One Chinese Buddhist monk named Faran
who sailed to India in the 4th century
in search of rare religious manuscripts
describes the perils and beauties of
this ocean.
In this sea there are many pirates. The
sea is boundless in extent. It is
impossible to know east or west and one
can only advance by observing the sun,
moon or stars. If it is dark rainy
weather, you have to follow the wind in
perfect uncertainty.
During the darkness of night, one only
sees the great waves striking each other
and shining like fire, whilst shors of
sea monsters of every description
surround the ship.
Today, the complex geography of this
region can prove confusing to many. As
you listen, if you find yourself getting
lost in the different names of islands
and seas referenced in this episode,
it's worth remembering that you're not
alone.
This is by far the densest region for
islands anywhere in the world. And in
fact, the government of Indonesia itself
has struggled to come up with a
definitive answer to exactly how many
islands there are within its borders.
One 2002 study using the satellite
images Landsat identified more than
18,000 islands, while another 2010 study
gave a lower figure, noting that only
around 9,000 even have names.
Nearly 90% of Indonesia's islands are
tiny, coming in at less than a kilometer
squared.
Other islands are massive.
The archipelago contains the world's
second largest island of Papua or New
Guinea, the third largest of Borneo, and
the sixth largest of Sumatra.
In land area, each of these is larger
than Japan or the size of the United
Kingdom and France combined.
But while this archipelago is home to
some enormous islands, these tend to be
rocky and mountainous, their interiors
covered in impenetrable rainforest, and
generally sparssely populated.
It is the fifth largest island in the
archipelago that has had perhaps the
greatest impact of all. And this is the
place where our story begins.
the long narrow island of Java.
Java is a volcanic island shaped like a
cigar running just south of and roughly
parallel to the equator.
It's little over 100 km wide north to
south, but stretches for more than a
thousand km east to west, and the center
of the island is dominated by a rocky
spine of conical volcanoes.
A medieval Javanese creation myth called
the Tanu Pangalaran describes how the
island was once floating free in the
ocean before the gods decided to nail it
down.
The island of Java was unsteady,
constantly moving up and down as it had
no great mountains, not to mention human
beings.
For this reason, Lord Jagat Prammana
arose and promptly performed yoga on the
island of Java.
The deity stood facing east. He churned
the water and it turned into foam and
turned into mountains.
For this reason, we have what is called
the land above the clouds. Now,
now the gods Brahma and Vishnu agreed
and made human beings. They needed lumps
of clay and formed them into humans of
perfect beauty.
Today, partly as a result of its rich
volcanic soil and its heavy rainfall and
strong sun, Java is the world's most
populous island.
It is home to more than 150 million
people. despite its land area being only
about the size of England, making it one
of the most densely populated places on
Earth.
More people live on Java than in the
whole of Russia, despite it being about
130 times smaller, and its capital of
Jakarta recently took the top spot as
the world's most populated city.
This reputation for abundance goes back
to ancient times.
The Hindu epic poem, the Ramayana,
written around 2,000 years ago, already
mentions Java as a place of wealth.
The island of Yava is decorated with
seven kingdoms, gold and silver islands
rich in gold mines and a cold mountain
that touches the sky with its peak.
Even in ancient times, the island had a
global reputation.
It was prominent enough in the 2n
century that the Greek writer and
geographer Claudius Tommy included it in
his work geographia
right at the farthest edge of the known
world.
He describes an island named Yabadu, a
name which he says means the island of
Bali, possibly referring to the hardy
grain millet, which has been an
important food stuff there for centuries
before the introduction of rice.
As a result of its inclusion in Tomy's
work, the island would also appear in a
number of medieval and early modern
mapundi or maps of the world. Although
few Europeans could agree on where
exactly the island was.
In these maps, it usually appears
somewhere wedged between Africa and Asia
and always as far away as it was
possible to get.
But for the people who lived on the
island of Java, it was the very center
of the world.
According to Javanese legend, it was
where the gods had first created
humanity and taught them the secrets of
civilization.
As the Tantu Pangaladan recounts,
such were the instructions of Lord Guru
to all the gods. They descended to Java.
The god Brahma became a blacksmith. The
earth served as his anvil, water as his
tongs, light as his fire, and wind as
his bellows and the sky as his hammer.
Lord Wiswakarma
descended as a carpenter and made a
house and people followed him and made
houses. The Lord Ishwara descended and
taught beneficial words in particular
about the 10 kinds of good conduct and
the five fields of learning.
Since it sits virtually on the equator,
Java experiences very little variation
in sunlight throughout the year.
In fact, its shortest day is only 48
minutes shorter than its longest.
The western side of the island also
enjoys very dependable monsoon rains
from the Indian Ocean, which combine
with the extremely fertile volcanic soil
so that farmers could grow all year
round and could often harvest three
whole crops of rice each year.
The 14th century Chinese source, the
Sunshi or History of the Sun Dynasty
describes the great abundance of this
island.
The country is flat and fit for
agriculture. Its products are rice,
hemp, and peas, there being no wheat.
Salt is obtained by boiling sea water
and there is an abundance of fish,
turtles, poultry, ducks, goats and
cattle which they kill for the purpose
of eating. Their fruit are papaya,
coconuts, plantains, sugarcane and taro.
From about the fifth century on, this
vast agricultural potential would give
birth to thriving societies and these
would go on to construct elaborate
monumental architecture.
For nearly the next thousand years, most
of these societies would arise in the
west of Java.
One king of this time named Pur Navaman
left one of the earliest stone
inscriptions carved into a large boulder
in the Chiruten River.
The powerful, illustrious and brave
king, the famous Por Navaran of the
Taruma Nagara Kingdom whose print of the
foot souls are the same as those of God
Vishnu.
The inscription is accompanied by a
carved imprint of both of the king's
feet, symbolically stamping his
ownership on the territory.
By the sixth or seventh century, a power
known as Kling seems to have risen up in
central Java and a description of it was
included in the Chinese source known as
the Sin Tang Shu or the new history of
the Tong Dynasty.
Carling is also called Java. It is
situated in the southern ocean. The
people make fortifications of wood and
even the largest houses are covered with
palm leaves. They have couches of ivory
and mats of the outer skin of bamboo.
The land produces tortois shell, gold
and silver, rhinoceros horns and ivory.
The country is very rich. They have
letters and are acquainted with
astronomy.
These early kingdoms seem to have met
with great success on the island of
Java, but little has survived of their
records, their literature, or their
architecture.
But all that would change with the
founding of a kingdom known as Mataram.
The name Martam comes from the Sanskrit
word martr meaning mother and likely
meant something like motherland.
This kingdom grew up not in the west but
in the highlands of central Java right
in the shadow of the great volcanoes
Merbu and Marappi.
The people of Mataram were the first to
truly take advantage of this mountainous
landscape and cultivated the steep
slopes of this area using concentric
terraces of rice fields fed and drained
by intricate systems of canals and
stonelined channels.
This kingdom of the mountains was
originally Hindu and worshiped primarily
the god Shiva, the god of creation and
destruction.
Living as they did on a land constantly
torn apart and remade by the destructive
power of the volcanoes, it's no mystery
why this god would have held sway in the
kingdom of Martam.
But with the rise of a dynasty known as
the Shilendras in the 8th century,
Martam began to drift further towards a
new religion, Buddhism.
In this period, Mataram would become
what's known to historians as an
Indianized Hindu Buddhist kingdom with
elements of both religions combined into
a syncratic whole.
These religions became so intertwined
over the centuries that followed that
the epic Tantu Pangaladan even recounts
the story of one god who came down to
earth and divided himself into two holy
sages, one Buddhist and one Hindu so
that he could spread both religions at
the same time.
Let us tell about Maampu Paleat.
He returned to the island of Java. He
divided his body into two and it became
a shyite and a Buddhist. Off they went
and arrived in Java. They headed for
Gira and set up a monastery together.
The kings of Java would even come to be
known by the title Bura Siwa Buddha
meaning the divine Lord Shiva Buddha. a
royal figure in whom the two sacred
beings were fused.
This was in general a period of
coexistence and unity. And it's in this
era that some of Java's most remarkable
monuments would be built.
The kings of the mountain kingdom of
Mataram were ambitious builders.
Around the year 850, they completed
construction of a great temple to Shiva,
the towering Pramanan temple, which
still sends its eight sturdy spires up
into the skies of southern Java.
It is the second largest Hindu structure
in Southeast Asia behind only anchor
watt in Cambodia and it left its mark
not just on the landscape but in the
name of the year in which its
construction was completed.
By this time, the Javanese had adopted a
unique system of naming each year,
giving them what are known as moon
chronogs or in Javanese Chundra sanka.
This system used the Indian Shaka
calendar which assigned numbers to the
years the way we do today like 1066,
1939 or 2026.
But the Javanese developed this Indian
calendar with their own poetic flourish.
They gave each number from 0 to 10 an
array of possible symbols like the sun,
moon, fire, and other elements which
they could choose from to give the year
a name that seemed the most fitting.
For example, the 18th century Balan
chronicle named the Babadgumi gives one
year the name Gaja Aappi Anin Watu or
elephant, fire, wind, stone due to a
particularly violent eruption of the
volcano Mount Aong that took place in
East Bali.
Another year in which a fierce battle
took place was named Paksha Shakara
Babumi or the force of violence moving
upon the earth.
Due to this system, we can sometimes get
a sense from the names that years were
given of the overriding mood in the
kingdom.
Sometimes a mood of joy and celebration,
at others of despair and sorrow.
On the year that the kings of Mataram
completed the Prammanan temple, they
were clearly proud of their achievement
and because of its eight towering main
shrines, they named the year in honor of
it. In our calendar it was 856
but in the Shaka calendar it was called
eight mountains of the holy monks as
recorded in a text known as the shavra
inscription.
In the time of the Shaka year, eight
mountains of the holy monks, the statue
of the god was finished and inaugurated.
After the shiva sanctuary had been
completed in its divine splendor, the
course of the river was changed so that
it rippled along the grounds.
Then the grounds were inaugurated as
temple grounds with the gods.
Other temples built by the kings of
Mataram, such as the sprawling temple at
Seu, are thought to have been Buddhist
since they were built in the form of a
mandala, an important geometrical
concept in Buddhism that is used to
conceptualize the shape of the universe.
But chief among their works is the
structure that would become what is
still the largest Buddhist temple in the
world.
It's thought that the Javanese of the
time called it Bumi Shambara Budara or
the mountain of combined virtues of the
10 stages of Buddhahood.
But today it is known by a name meaning
only the great Buddha or Boro Buddhur.
Boro Budur rises like a mountain from
the river plains right in the shadow of
the great volcano Mount Marappi.
This vast complex consists of nine
stacked platforms rising like a wedding
cake up to a height of 35 m and topped
by a central dome.
One heritage worker Gerard Bolla
describes the appearance of this
incredible temple.
Orodor the mountain of the virtues is
first of all a landscape. The landscape
which over a thousand years ago met the
eyes of those who came on pilgrimage
here to seek inner peace. It has hardly
changed. In the distance, two volcanoes,
one ever menacing, glows red in the
night. All around in the middle
distance, a ring of mountains built on
this same volcanic stone. Borobodor
emerges from a delicate green background
of tropical vegetation.
The design of Bora Budur like the temple
at Su is an enormous mandala visible
from above.
But this mandala covers the area of two
football pitches and guides its pilgrims
up through a series of concentric
walkways and stairways carved out of
black volcanic stone.
These are all lined with nearly 3,000
carved freezes and 500 Buddha statues
created by the finest craftsmen the
kingdom could find.
The archaeologist, Professor Raden
Sokmano, who was in charge of the
project to restore the great temple in
modern times, describes its spiritual
function.
For the ardent Buddhist, it is the
highest wisdom that leads to the
ultimate salvation. And for the
technician, the highest degree of
expertise that leads to the appropriate
fulfillment of his duty. In both cases,
Boro Budor is the embodiment of such a
deeply felt wish. It is a prayer in
stone.
The symbolism of this structure shaped
like a mountain would likely have been
obvious to the early medieval Javanese.
The gods had once placed the mountains
of Java to secure the island in place
and bring stability to the land.
Now their king did the same thing.
placing his own mountain on the
landscape to act as a testament to the
lasting stability of his reign.
And Bora Budor was built to last.
It was constructed entirely without
mortar or cement, carving its 2 million
blocks of volcanic stone into intricate
interlocking shapes to hold them
together.
This design has meant that it has
largely survived the countless
earthquakes that have taken place over
the last millennium in one of the
world's most seismically active zones,
as well as the shifting ground beneath
their feet. The builders also had the
heavy rainfall of the Javanese monsoon
to contend with. For this reason, they
equipped the site of Bora Budur with
more than 100 spouts for drainage, each
carved in the shape of a giant or sea
dragon, so that when it rained, water
would have poured from their mouths.
But the most remarkable and haunting
feature of this monument is the
thousands of reliefs carved all around
its galleries.
Many of these carvings show stories from
the lives of the Buddha ascending
through kilometers of galleries. And in
this way, the monument is a story
brought to life in stone.
But alongside this religious narrative,
others show scenes of simple daily life
for all the different levels of Javanese
society.
In these carvings, we see people
carrying woven baskets for winnowing and
steaming rice and stirring milk rice in
pots. We see people working in the
fields and shopping in a bustling urban
marketplace.
People carrying baskets of tropical
fruit and nets full of fish. All of
their faces looking out from the stone,
frozen in a moment that passed by more
than a thousand years ago.
The Chinese history of Leyang describes
the dress and appearance of the people
of Java which can be seen in the reliefs
of Boro Buddhur.
Men and women have the upper part of the
body naked. Their hair hangs loosely
down and around their lower limbs they
only use a sarong of cotton. The king
and the nobles have a thin flowered
cloth for covering the upper part of
their body. They wear a girdle of gold
and golden rings in their ears. Young
girls cover themselves with a cloth of
cotton and wear an embroidered girdle.
In these carvings, we also get a sense
for courtly life.
We see the king coming and going on his
elephant, his courtiers and the palace
women.
In some carvings, we see the king and
his nobles enjoying a splendid feast
known as a mahammansa.
One 12th century Javanese epic poem
known as the bulman taka or death of
Bulma describes the sumptuous sight of
one of these feasts.
The dishes were salted eggs, the pork
neck cuts, ayong ayong and paban,
vegetables in hot sauce, lickin and
chzecha, red mints of tripe with its
various red salads and sizzling dripping
of turtle
and the boiled vegetables. Languban with
marrow and tongue in rolls. Mushrooms
steamed in leaves. Crisp flakes of
jellyfish. Liver with rump accompanied
by roasted lungs. Breast bone.
Intestines on skewers with fat and hot
kebabs.
The banana heart was sweet. And there
was no lack of prawns, crabs, salted
fish, and muscles. Pickled meats,
grilled meats, wuku, and various
skewered meats, doves, puk birds, and
wild pigeon made them clutch in all
directions.
ring aarab.
>> Some of these 9th century carvings even
depict recipes that are still enjoyed in
Indonesia today. Among them, a dish
called tonang, a tall cone of rice
surrounded by side dishes which is still
prepared for special occasions.
But one particular feature of these
carvings has always captured the
imagination of those who visit the
ruins.
These are the so-called Boro Budor
ships.
In among the scenes of daily life are
carved the shapes of five large seagoing
vessels, graceful and high-sided, which
show just how accomplished the Javanese
had become as shipbuilders and sailors.
And so it's no surprise that it was
around this time that the people of Java
began to gain a reputation around the
world as traders and pirates.
The Javanese of the Mataram period
sailed in large ships that were often
built from teik.
This kind of wood was prized for its
strength and its high oil content which
gives it a natural water resistance even
without varnishing and gives it a
distinct rich aroma like fine leather.
These ships were built without nails
using only interlocking joints and
wooden dowels and with ingenious
arrangements of sails.
The 3rd century Chinese writer Wan Chen
in his work Nanju Yiu J or strange
things of the southern lands describes
the sight of these majestic vessels.
The people sometimes rig as many as four
sails which they carry in a row from bow
to stern. The four sails do not face
directly forward, but are set obliquely
and so arranged that they can all be
fixed in the same direction to receive
the wind and to spill it. If it is
violent, the sailors diminish or augment
the surface of the sails according to
the conditions. Thus these ships sail
without avoiding strong winds and
dashing waves by the aid of which they
can make great speed.
To Wan Chen and other Chinese writers,
these Javanese ships were so remarkable
because China itself would not develop
large oceangoing vessels until around
the 9th century or 600 years later.
In fact, the Chinese held the ships of
these islanders in such reverence that
no foreign craft were permitted to sail
within range of the main port of
Guangong or Canton. As the 16th century
Portuguese diplomat Tom Perez recounts,
"They say that the Chinese made this law
about not being able to go to Canton for
fear of the Japanese and Malays, for it
is certain that one of these people
ships would route 20 Chinese ships. Such
is their fear of Malays and Japanese."
This fear appears to have been
warranted.
The inscriptions of the Cham people of
Vietnam and the Camair in Cambodia
frequently reference the arrival of
fearsome seagoing raiders who are
thought to have sailed from islands like
Sumatra and Java.
One inscription in the Po Nagar temple
in Vietnam describes one such raid in
the year 774.
Ferocious, pitiles, dark-skinned men
born in other countries whose food was
more horrible than corpses and who were
vicious and furious came in ships, took
away the temple statue and set fire to
the temple.
The Javanese were in part able to become
such successful sailors due to the
extremely predictable wind patterns that
take place in this part of the world.
During the rainy season from December to
March, the winds blow in over Java from
the Asian mainland in the northwest,
picking up moisture over the South China
Sea and Pacific Ocean and bringing the
monsoon.
But during the dry season from April to
September, the winds reverse direction
and blow from the southeast and the
deserts of Australia, bringing dry air
and a lower probability of rain.
This meant you could travel whichever
direction you wanted so long as you
wisely chose your season to sail.
As their confidence grew on the waves,
we have evidence that the Javanese also
undertook some even more ambitious
voyages.
One Italian explorer who arrived in Java
around 1505 named Ludovvic Deva of
Bologna sailed to the island of Java and
was amazed to see the captain of the
ship navigate even when the North Star
was no longer visible.
When the chartered vessel was supplied
with provisions, we took our way towards
the beautiful island called Java at
which we arrived in 5 days sailing
towards the south. My companion asked
the Christians, "Now that we have lost
the North Star, how does he steer us? Is
there any other North Star than this by
which we steer?" The Christians asked
the captain of the ship this same thing,
and he showed us four or five stars,
among which there was one which he said
was the opposite to our north star.
This was the socalled southern cross,
the distinctive pattern of stars that
could be seen in the southern hemisphere
in the direction of the South Pole.
The Europeans were amazed at this
discovery. But the captain then told him
that the Javanese had sailed into the
south following these stars and had
there come upon an icy and frozen land.
He also told us that on the other side
of the said island towards the south,
there are some other races who navigate
by the said four or five stars opposite
to ours. And moreover, they gave us to
understand that beyond the said island,
the day does not last more than 4 hours,
and that there it was colder than in any
other part of the world.
If this is true, it means that the
Javanese had already sailed to and
around Australia and set out into the
Antarctic Ocean.
But tantalizingly, we have only this
secondhand story to go by, and the rest
will have to be left to our
imaginations.
But as the centuries of the first
millennium went on, there is a great
deal more evidence that the people of
Java were making their mark in even
further lands.
7,000 km away on the shores of East
Africa, the 10th century Persian writer
Bazour Iben Shari gives an account of a
series of raids undertaken by a people
from a faraway land that he calls the
Wacwack.
The Wacwack set out with a thousand
ships to launch a determined attack upon
the town of Kbala.
But they were unable to capture it for
the town was strongly fortified and was
surrounded by an arm of the sea in the
midst of which Kbarlo rose like a
fortress.
When the people of the African coast
eventually came to terms with the
attackers, they learned more about why
they had come and how far they had
traveled.
The people of that country demanded why
they had come to Gmbalo rather than to
any other place. They replied that it
was because the country possessed
merchandise of value in the Wacwack
country and in China such as ivory,
tortoise shell, panther skins, and
amberes. And also because they wanted to
obtain some of the Zenge people who
being strong men are able to stand heavy
labor. Their voyage, they said, had
lasted a year. If the story told by
these people be true, this proves that
the Wacwack Islands are situated
opposite to China.
The location of these Wacwack Islands
has long been debated.
One clue can be found in the Persian
chronicler Iben Kodadbe, whose
description has made many historians
believe that they may have been the
islands of Indonesia.
East of China are the lands of Wacwack,
which are so rich in gold that the
inhabitants make the chains for their
dogs and the collars for their monkeys
of this metal. They manufacture tunics
woven with gold. Excellent. Ebony wood
is found there. Gold and ebony are
exported from Wacwack.
This detail of dogs wearing collars made
of gold was also mentioned by early
European explorers who visited Java,
leading many to conclude that the
Wacwack really were Javanese.
If this story does relate an attack on
eastern Africa by the people of Java,
then it shows the extent of their ship
building and seafaring prowess and that
they have become a formidable threat for
all the peoples who lived around the
Indian Ocean.
From these raids, they would have
brought back gold, ivory, and slaves to
Java.
But in other places, they didn't simply
raid and sail away.
In the large island of Madagascar, just
off the coast of Eastern Africa, the
people's language has always puzzled
linguists.
The Madagascan language of Malagasi
shares little in common with those of
the African mainland. And it was only
when the grammar and syntax were
compared with Indonesian languages that
a remarkable similarity was noticed.
Although separated by the entire Indian
Ocean, the language of Malagasi shares a
grammatical structure with several
Indonesian languages like Javanese. And
they even have a number of different
words in common.
Just one example is the word for island,
nosi in Malagasi and Nusa in Japanese.
In fact, the closest living relative of
Malagasi is thought to be a language
called Manan, which originated on the
south coast of Borneo.
The most modern analysis of
mitochondrial DNA in Madagascar has
confirmed this connection and shows that
the people there can trace their lineage
back to about 30 mothers who arrived on
the island from what is now Indonesia.
This suggests a single boatload of
settlers who had traveled across one of
the world's widest oceans to find a new
home. They also brought plants and crops
with them.
Botists estimate that a full 7% of the
plant life on Madagascar today
originated in Indonesia.
These include bananas, plantains, taro,
and yams. And all of these were already
well established there by the medieval
period.
In602,
another Portuguese explorer, Dio Duto,
described these far-reaching journeys of
the Javanese.
The Javanese are all men very
experienced in the art of navigation to
the point that they claim to be the most
ancient of all. It is certain that they
formally navigated to Africa's Cape of
Good Hope and were in communication with
the east coast of the island of
Madagascar where there are many brown
and Javaneseike natives who say they are
descended from them.
The Javanese of this period navigated
using the stars but also magnetic
compasses and maps written on the bark
of the paper Malbury tree.
In 1512, only 20 years after Columbus
had first reached the Americas and 12
years after the first Europeans set foot
in Brazil, a Portuguese concistador
fighting on the Malay Peninsula captured
a sea chart from a Javanese sailor. He
was amazed to find that it had already
been updated with all the new
discoveries that had been made on the
other side of the world. as he wrote in
one letter to King Manuel I of Portugal.
>> We found a large map of a Javanese pilot
containing the Cape of Good Hope,
Portugal and the land of Brazil, the Red
Sea and the Sea of Persia, the Clove
Islands, the navigation of the Chinese
and Japanese, and how the kingdoms
border on each other. It seems to me,
sir, that this was the best thing I have
ever seen. and your highness will be
very pleased to see it.
>> In 2003, a modern team was able to pilot
a replica of an old Japanese sailing
ship from Indonesia to Madagascar and
around the Cape of Good Hope in South
Africa. Thus proving that this journey
was possible with the technology
available at the time.
But despite its remarkable achievements
in architecture and its voyages of
discovery, the Chileendra dynasty of
Mataram would eventually decline and all
of its grand monuments would decline
with it.
The reasons for the fall of Mataram are
unclear since no true chronicles have
survived from this time. But the
kingdom's decline may have been related
to a series of dramatic volcanic
eruptions that occurred sometime in the
10th and early 11th centuries.
The people of Java have always lived
with a particular paradox
that the immense productivity of their
land also comes from its most
destructive force.
Many landscapes that experience a
monsoon season as heavy as Java can
suffer from poor soil quality as the
seasonal rains wash away top soil and
leech nutrients away.
But in much of Java, the hundreds of
active volcanoes counteract this effect.
Due to the island's particular geology,
its volcanoes are especially beneficial
for the soil, filling it with minerals
like magnesium, potassium, and
phosphorus that plants thrive on, all
blasted out of the depths of the earth
itself.
Volcanic soil is also uniquely porous
and retains moisture exceptionally well,
while allowing air circulation for plant
roots.
But of course, a volcano is a violent
phenomenon.
When they erupt, they scorch the earth
with pyrolastic flows, spew lava, and
rain huge boulders down from the sky
across a large area.
This poses an obvious problem that the
areas of the greatest agricultural
productivity on the island were also the
most dangerous.
This meant that while the volcano's
overall effect on the island was
positive, a year in which a great
eruption took place could wipe out a
good proportion of any kingdom's food
supplies.
And of all these volcanoes, by far the
most active was the one that the
Javanese call by a name which means the
mountain of fire or merap.
Rising to nearly 3,000 m or 10,000 ft.
Mount Marappi is the most active volcano
in the whole of Indonesia and is
considered one of the most active and
dangerous in the world.
It has erupted regularly for at least
the last 500 years with small eruptions
occurring every 2 to 3 years and larger
ones every 10 to 15.
Then every few hundred years the
mountain explodes in a truly
catastrophic fashion.
The Javanese Chronicle, the Babad Tan
Jawi, records the devastation caused by
one eruption of the great Mount Marappi
that took place in the 16th century.
Then Mount Marappi erupted with fire. It
made a terrifying thundering noise. A
rain of ash fell. A volcanic mud flow
ran down the OAC river. Big rocks rose
from the flow and landed on the land.
When the piles of wood on the Ganang GD
mountains were set on fire, the
mountains became a blaze of fire. The
Gong Ki Bichchuk was beaten ceaselessly.
All tried to save their lives and ran in
all directions.
Added to this obvious physical
destruction, the Javanese also held the
volcanoes in great spiritual reverence
and viewed eruptions as signs and
portants from the gods.
After the deaths of great kings,
Javanese chronicles often describe the
mountains rumbling in mourning.
At the death of his majesty, the wailing
in the palace was as loud as thunder.
Mount Marappi rumbled,
joining in with the sound of a
rainstorm.
It was believed that the eruptions,
earthquakes, and various rumblings of
the land were not just seismic events,
but actually one of the primary ways
that the gods weighed in on the affairs
of humanity.
For this reason, their timing could have
real life or death consequences.
One chronicle recounts the story of a
lucky prisoner held by a 17th century
Javanese king.
The king wanted to kill the prisoner
Raden Masuya Kasuma. But this did not
happen because every time they wanted to
kill him, Mount Marrapy flared up with a
terrifying noise. In the end, the man
was set free and promoted and given the
lordship of 1,000 rice fields.
A particularly devastating eruption
would not only cause immense economic
damage to the kingdom, it could also be
considered a clear sign that the gods
were angry with the current ruler. For
any king who didn't have a firm grasp on
power, this could be a devastating blow.
From some inscriptions left in Java, we
know that as the 9th century came to an
end, the kingdom of Mataram descended
into civil war with three kings ruling
in only two years.
When the dust of this civil war settled
in the year 929,
a king named Rakhino Pusindok took to
the throne. But curiously, it seems the
kingdom of Mataram had by this point
moved.
All of the inscriptions issued by this
king would be written in East Java, far
away from its original heartlands around
the volcano Mount Marappi.
It seems that around the beginning of
the 10th century, the entire Mataram
Kingdom simply upped sticks and fled its
original wealthy province, leaving its
towering temples and cities abandoned.
And what's perhaps most significant is
that no other power seems to have swept
in to the empty lands. This suggests
that some kind of cataclysm took place
there.
Archaeological evidence shows that the
early 10th century layer of human
occupation at the great temple of Boro
Budor, for instance, is sealed by up to
half a meter of volcanic ash, suggesting
a major eruption.
The peoples of this land were no
strangers to erupting volcanoes.
So we can imagine that it must have
taken one of particular violence or a
series of eruptions taking place in
frighteningly quick succession to cause
the wholesale abandonment of this
kingdom and its reestablishment hundreds
of kilometers to the east.
One inscription known as the Puchangan
stone describes a kind of disaster
sweeping the land.
In the time of the great catastrophe
that overwhelmed the island of Java in
the Saka year 928 when King Warari came
forth from Waram, the whole of Java
seemed transformed into a single raging
sea.
Many of the foremost men of the realm
perished. Chief among the dead was the
divine king.
Unfortunately, the exact dating of
volcanic eruptions is difficult, and
it's hard to say whether this was truly
the cause of Mataram's downfall.
But whether from volcanic causes or not,
it's clear that for one reason or
another, life had become unlivable for
the people of Matarang in central Java.
The kingdom eventually reached a level
of stability in its new home in East
Java, away from the destruction it had
faced.
But its confidence in itself and in the
god's approval of its rulers had been
fatally reduced.
Within a century, the remains of Martam
was facing destruction, now at the hands
of human enemies.
An invasion by a neighboring king wiped
out what was left of it, and the kingdom
of Mataram disappeared,
living on only in the stone carvings
left lining the walls of its great
temples. Thousands of moments of
everyday life now sealed beneath a thick
layer of volcanic ash.
After the fall of Mataram, a number of
successor kingdoms would rise up.
In the 11th century, much of Java was
reunited again under the rule of a king
named Ayalanga, whose name meant he who
leapt over the water.
He was born on the small island of Bali
and crossed the sea to Java as a young
man.
The Puchangan stone describes how this
king was spared from the destruction
that swept the land during the fall of
Mataram.
>> At that time, his majesty was only 16
years old, still too young to have
mastered the art of war. Yet because he
was the very manifestation of Vishnu,
all the gods protected him from being
swept away by the great destruction.
Arlanga would rule successfully for
several decades. But when he died, the
land divided again.
The kingdom that would truly give birth
to Java's golden era was named
Singasari.
Singari derived its name from the
Sanskrit word simha meaning lion. And
this lion kingdom was founded by a king
named Ken Angro.
Ken Angro's name means the man who
overturned everything. and he was a
revolutionary force on Java.
In the centuries since he lived, the
legend of Ken Angro has grown to mythic
proportions and he has inspired theater,
song and poetry in Indonesia.
The story of his life is largely told in
a fragmentaryary chronicle known as the
Paraton
or the book of kings written sometime
later in the 16th century.
According to this chronicle, Ken Angraok
was actually the son of the Hindu god
Brahma who appeared to his mother, a
poor woman named Ken Endok, and informed
her of her immaculate conception.
The god Brahma descended there and lay
with Ken Endoc.
This meeting took place in the fields of
Lalaten. The god made a vow with the
woman. You must not go to your husband
again. If you lie with him, he will die
and my child will be corrupted. That
child is named Ken Anbrook and he will
one day rule the land of Java. With
that, Brahma vanished.
The woman held true to her word and soon
Ken Angro was born.
But the family was extremely poor and
couldn't provide for the little boy.
His parents abandoned him in a grave.
But he was found by a common thief named
Lemong who was perhaps plundering the
graveyard for valuables.
When her time was full, she gave birth
to a boy. Ken Endok abandoned him in a
burial ground for children. Not long
after, a thief named Len Bong wandered
into the same place. There he saw
something glowing. Drawn to it, he heard
the sound of a child crying. When he
came closer, he saw that the light was
coming from the child himself. Lemong
picked him up, carried him home, and
raised him as his own son.
Brought up by this thief, Ken Angro
would learn all the tricks of his trade
until he was the most accomplished thief
in Java.
But one day he met an Indian holy man
who identified him as the son of Brahma
and an embodiment of the god Vishnu.
This holy man convinced Ken Angro to
give up his sinful life.
As a reward, Ken Angro gained a magical
weapon, a kind of Javanese knife known
as ais.
These are long daggers often created
with a distinctive rippled blade and
they were worn by Javanese men as a sign
of status as a talisman against various
evils and of course as a practical
sidearm for self-defense.
One Chinese visitor to Java at the start
of the 15th century named Mahuan writes
about the importance of these blades.
From little boys of 3 years to old men
of a hundred years, they all have these
knives which are all made of steel with
most intricate patterns drawn in very
delicate lines. For the handles, they
use gold or rhinoceros horn or
elephant's teeth engraved with
representations of human forms or
devil's faces. The craftsmanship being
very fine and skillful.
With this magical sword by his side, Ken
Angro rose to prominence in Java and
eventually through the overwhelming
force of his various virtues became its
king as the paraton describes.
Not long afterwards, Ken Anro was
acclaimed as king of Tamapel. His realm
was called Singasari.
His enthronement was witnessed by
learned men of both the Shyite and
Buddhist traditions of Keri.
Those who had once shown Ken Angarok
kindness in his days of hardship were
summoned, granted protection, and
generously rewarded for their loyalty.
Bilazani.
>> Not everyone easily accepted the rule of
this commoner.
In the nearby rival kingdom of Kediri,
the king was named Dandang Gendis and he
refused to accept Ken Angro as his king.
Dandang Gendis gathered his armies and
marched to fight Ken Angro.
But he was no match for the divine power
of the God made man.
>> He fell because he was attacked on all
sides by the forces of Singasari who
came on like a flood pouring down from
the mountains. The army of Keri
scattered like a swarm of bees, fleeing
in panic, abandoning the field like
startled goats, casting aside their
parasolles.
King Dandang Dendis withdrew from the
battle and fled into the realm of the
gods, rising up into the air with his
horse, his grooms, his parasolbearers,
and those who carried his drinking
vessels and his mats. All of them
ascending into the sky. Thus, Kendiri
was utterly defeated by Ken Angbrook.
Needless to say, this section of the
Paraton Chronicle is considered to be
largely mythical and reflects the
propaganda of this king's new regime.
But this story would be repeated across
the towns and villages of Java by
trained storytellers who together wo a
new national myth around the figure of
Ken Angro.
One of the most important mediums in
which this story was told was that of
the Javanese shadow puppets.
The exact origin of Javanese shadow
puppetry is a mystery, but it's clear
from a number of oblique references in
Javanese literature that it was already
a wellestablished practice by at least
the 10th century.
This form of shadow theater is known as
Wyang.
Wang in Javanese means shadow or ghost,
but it can also mean imagination.
And these plays would retell stories
from the Hindu epics like the Mahabarat,
local Javanese stories such as how rice
came to the earth and the stories of
their kings and ancestors.
The Chinese visitor to Java at the
beginning of the 15th century, Marwan,
describes witnessing these performances.
Each time the performer unrolls and
exposes a section of the picture, he
thrusts it forward toward the audience
and speaking with a loud voice in the
foreign language, he explains the
derivation of this section. The crowd
sits around and listens to him,
sometimes laughing, sometimes crying,
exactly as if the narrator were reciting
one of our popular romances.
These shadow plays would typically start
at nightfall and go on until dawn and
would be conducted behind a screen of
white cotton fabric using a lamp burning
with coconut oil, usually cast in metal
in the form of the sacred bird Gauda.
The puppets were typically made of goat
hide or buffalo skin mounted on bamboo
canes and placed in a trunk of banana
palm lying behind the screen.
The puppets had jointed limbs and were
punctured all over with intricate
patterns of holes that allowed the light
through so that their shadows could then
be cast onto a screen.
These puppet shows were often
accompanied by music.
>> In small village performances, this
could simply be the drumming of the
puppeteer on the box where the puppets
were kept.
But in the royal court, a puppeteer
would perform alongside a full orchestra
of musicians known as a gamalan with a
whole host of 15 instruments.
These night-long plays would unfold
according to strict traditions.
In the hours between sunset and
midnight, the puppeteer introduced the
characters and set up the conflict. And
then at the stroke of midnight, the
drama burst out into a frenzied clash
between good and evil.
The Portuguese traveler and apothecary
Tomé Perez, who visited Java around
1513,
wrote about seeing these forms of
theater and shadow puppetry.
The land of Java is a land of performers
and masks of various Japanese kinds, and
both men and women do thus. They have
entertainments of dancing and stories.
They mime. They wear actors dresses and
all their clothes. They are certainly
graceful. They have music of bells. The
sound of all of them playing together is
like an organ. These actors show a
thousand graces like these by day and
night. At night, they make shadows of
various shapes.
Over time, the performance of these
shadow plays took on a spiritual
meaning.
The puppeteer or dalang was thought to
become possessed by the power of the
gods as he worked. And in the
performance all the holy elements were
represented.
The banana palm representing the earth,
the cloth screen, the sky, the fire in
the coconut oil lamp, and of course, the
interplay of light and darkness, good
and evil, as the stories of gods and
demons played out across the screen.
These performances were considered to
have real power. Some such as the
Bratayuta or a Javanese version of the
Indian epic the Mahabarat were
considered too potent to ever perform in
their entirety. As Thomas Stamford
Raffles records,
although the Wyang may represent any
portion of the Bratuda, there is a
prevalent superstition that a great war
will be the inevitable consequence of
performing at one sitting the whole of
this poem. It is gravely asserted that a
chief of Kendall tried this experiment
about 50 years ago, but that the
performance was no sooner completed than
his country was laid to waste and
destroyed.
Other of these shadow plays were
performed at auspicious times in order
to bring about certain effects with
stories of the goddess of rice told
during the harvests and the great myths
told during times of trouble and strife.
One particular shadow play was reserved
solely for times when a plague of mice
or rats had descended on a village, and
its goal was to convince the rodents to
depart and dwell in the kingdom of
vermin instead.
Over
the next centuries, the story of Ken
Angro, the first king of Singer Sari,
would be told again and again in these
kinds of performances and would take on
more and more fantastical elements.
And for that reason, it's impossible to
say definitively which parts may have a
grain of truth to them. But it's likely
that some elements are true. That Ken
Angro was a common man of uncertain
birth and lineage. That he had been a
thief or brigand of some kind. That he
rose to power in the kingdom in a
violent upheaval and crushed the nearby
kingdom of Kadiri in open battle.
But after he comes to the throne, the
tone of the chronicle shifts and becomes
more grounded in historical reality.
Many events recorded during his reign
are dated. And so this second half of
the chronicle is considered to contain
more historically verifiable
information.
What we know for sure is that over the
course of the 13th century, Ken Angro's
new kingdom of Singari would gradually
expand its power, wealth, and prestige.
But it was under the reign of his
greatgrandson, the fifth king of
Singari, that it would grow into a true
empire. His name was King Keranagara.
And during his time on the throne, he
would order expeditions to extend the
kingdom's influence not just over most
of Java, but across the sea to the large
island of Borneo to the north, the small
island of Bali to the east, and even
conduct a successful invasion of Java's
sister island of Sumatra in the
northwest.
Now the kingdom of Singari had grown to
be a true seagoing empire and it
controlled virtually all of the region's
most crucial waterways.
And the most important of these was the
narrow sea corridor known as the
straight of Malaka.
The Malay Peninsula is a long body of
land that stretches southeast from the
southern edge of the Asian continent
where Thailand meets Malaysia.
And just off its southernmost point and
following the line of the continental
shelf is the island of Sumatra and then
Java.
Together, these form a sea wall of more
than 3,000 km that stands between the
Indian Ocean and the South Pacific and
South China Sea.
In this massive wall, there are only two
narrow gates. The southerntherly one
known as the Straits of Sunda and the
northern one, the Straits of Malaka.
The American sailor and writer Herman
Melville writing in the mid 19th century
describes the sight of these straits.
Those narrow straits of Sunda stand
midway in that vast rampart of islands
like the central gateway opening into
some vast walled empire.
the inexhaustible wealth of spices and
silks and jewels and gold and ivory with
which the thousand islands of that
oriental sea are enriched are thus
guarded from the all grasping western
world.
For much of history, it has been the
wider and deeper straight of Malaca that
has been used most heavily.
In fact, today it is the busiest
shipping channel in the world, seeing
nearly 100,000 ships pass through it
each year.
Around a quarter of all global trade
passes through this narrow waterway,
where the massive cities of Singapore
and Koala Lumpur are today located.
And in the 13th century during the time
of the singari kingdom this waterway was
no less crucial or lucrative.
Around the year 1515, the Portuguese
diplomat to Perez passed through the
Yemen port of Aiden on the Red Sea and
wrote that goods transported thousands
of miles from Malaca featured
prominently in the city's markets where
merchants would carry them on to Egypt
and from there into Europe.
The merchants from Cairo bring the
merchandise which comes from Italy and
Greece and Damascus to Aiden. While the
merchants of Aiden take back with them
all the products of Malaca, cloves,
nutmeg, mace, sandalwood, Brazil wood,
silks, seed pearls, musk, porcelain, and
other things.
Control
of the narrow waterway of the Malaca
strait gave King Keranagardada immense
power despite the relatively small size
of the kingdom of Singasari.
Now, anyone wishing to sail between
China and India or the rest of the world
either did so with Kerta Nagada's
permission or had to take a detour of at
least 2,000 km through rough and stormy
seas around this island wall.
As a result of this control, the power
and wealth of Singer Sari grew
dramatically.
But there were much larger empires in
the region who had a strong interest in
making sure that the flow of goods by
sea could pass through these narrow
straits.
And as the 13th century came to an end,
the kingdom of Singari came into direct
conflict with one of these much larger
powers.
In the year 1289,
King Keranagara of the Javanese Kingdom
of Singari received a group of
ambassadors at his court.
They came finely dressed, horty, and
proud, and said that they had come to
speak on behalf of the world's most
powerful man.
That was the Mongol Emperor of China,
Kubla Khn.
As we saw in our 19th episode, from
their humble beginnings on the Mongolian
step, over the last century, the Mongols
had embarked on a remarkable series of
campaigns to conquer all of China,
Persia, and the Middle East, along with
much of what is today Russia, and
Eastern Europe.
Founded by the warlord Chingis Khan, the
Mongol Empire was the largest contiguous
land empire in history and combined the
speed and power of Mongol horsemen with
the craftsmanship of Persia and the
ingenuity and manpower of China.
By this point, the enormous Mongol
Empire had split into four separate
domains. But the largest of these was
still the world's biggest empire at the
time.
That was the one ruled from China by the
grandson of Chingis Khan, the emperor
Kubla.
This hybrid Chinese Mongolian power was
known as the Yuan dynasty.
But by this time, the empire had begun
to struggle.
The emperor Kubli was now well into his
70s and his domain was plagued by
political and economic problems.
The Mongol Empire had been built on
conquest, but now its terrifying engine
seemed to have run out of fuel. 8 years
earlier, Kubla's forces had for the
second time failed to capture a foothold
on the islands of Japan. His invasions
of Burma and Vietnam had also fizzled
out with the Mongol forces struggling in
the tropical heat.
The aging Mongol Emperor desperately
needed a victory, and he had been
increasingly casting his gaze southwards
across the sea and towards the wealthy
island of Java.
The Chinese chronicle, the Yuani, or
History of Yuan, describes this strange
and farway land.
The customs and products of this land
are not much known, but as a rule, the
barbarian countries over the sea produce
many rare and valuable things which
fetch a high price in China. The
inhabitants are strange and their nature
and speech are not understood by the
Chinese.
By that time, Java's kingagara
had been defying Kubla Khan for nearly a
decade.
Two previous ambassadorial visits to his
court had been sent home without any
tribute for the Mongol Khn, and the
defiance of this small island was
beginning to make the empire look weak.
For this reason, in 1289,
Kubla sent a new party of envoys to Java
to meet with the king and give him a
final ultimatum.
They demanded that King Kerton swear an
oath of feelalty to the Mongol Emperor,
pay him a hefty tribute, and send
members of his royal family to the
Mongol court in China to act as
hostages.
But when these ambassadors arrived, they
would not find King Keranagara in an
agreeable mood.
The Javanese of the time considered
repeated requests of this kind to be
exceedingly rude.
To Perez writes about the proud nature
of the Javanese people.
The Japanese are men who if they write
once and do not get a reply, do not
write again. Although it may be of great
importance to them, the Japanese are
daring men and determined to die. They
are gamblers and play for high stakes.
King Keranagara was no different and he
would now make a tremendous gamble for
the highest stakes possible.
He ordered that the Mongol ambassadors
be punished.
By some accounts, their faces were
branded with hot irons and their ears
cut off, a punishment typically reserved
for bandits and pirates.
We can only imagine the rage of the
Mongol Emperor Kubla Khn upon hearing
this news and seeing the mutilated faces
of his ambassadors.
The history of Yuan describes what
happened next.
In the second month of the 29th year of
the Yuan dynasty, the emperor issued an
order to the governor of Fujen,
directing him to send an army to subdue
Java, to collect soldiers to the number
of 20,000, to send out a thousand ships,
and to equip them with provisions for a
year and with 40,000 bars of silver.
The emperor said to them, "When you
arrive at Java, you must clearly
proclaim that they have lately cut the
face of the imperial envoy, Mongchi, and
that you have come to punish them."
This expedition set sail 3 years later
in the year 1292,
but it was to be a difficult voyage.
The history of Yuan describes the
troubles they encountered on the Java
Sea.
The wind was strong and the sea very
rough so that the ships rolled heavily
and the soldiers could not eat for many
days. The forces to attack Java were
driven by the wind to one island and
many ships were wrecked. Over a hundred
men who were ill from the long beating
about in the storm were unable to leave
with the rest of the expedition and were
left there. And today the Chinese live
mixed up with the native families.
Despite their troubles on the voyage,
the Mongol forces eventually arrived on
the shores of Java in the next year of
1293,
ready to punish King Keranagara for
defying the empire and mistreating its
ambassadors.
But when they arrived, they would find
their enthusiasm for revenge had been
somewhat deflated.
In fact, in the preceding year, the
defiant kingagara
had been overthrown and killed by a
usurper named Ja Katon.
Ja Katon was the ruler of a city called
Kediri, which controlled a province
covering much of central Java.
For a long time, Kadiri had actually
been the predominant power on the
island. But after its king, Dandan
Gendis had been defeated in battle by
the hero Ken Angro, Kadiri had been
eclipsed by the rise of Singari.
Now Kadiri was a vassel of King
Keranagara
but it was by far the most powerful of
his subjects and as a result never sat
comfortably within his kingdom.
The epic poem the Deshavanana describes
the new ruler of Kadiri Ja Katon as
cunning and malevolent.
There was a vassal king, a villain known
by the name of Ja Katong, who there in
the land of Kadiri desired to replace
the king and was outstandingly clever at
laying schemes.
At the time, the majority of King
Keranagara's forces were away from Java,
fighting to increase his territory
across the sea in Sumatra. And so, Ja
Katon saw his chance.
According to the Paraton or Book of
Kings, Jaakong was encouraged to seize
the opportunity by one of his allies who
sent him a thinly veiled message.
The secret letter said, "My lord, I
respectfully tell you if his majesty has
any consideration and desire to hunt.
Now his majesty has the chance to so
hunt. It will be the best and the most
opportune moment. There is no danger.
There are no tigers, wild buffaloos, nor
snakes, or even thorns. There is only
one tiger, but it has no teeth.
Urged on by this coded message, King
Jayak rose in rebellion.
His city of Kadiri was not far from the
capital of Singari,
but it was on the other side of a number
of towering volcanic cones, mounts
Kellud, Arjuna, and Kawi.
to strike at Singari and depose the
king. He could either march north
through the easier territory of the
northern plains or south through the
rugged hill country riven by gorges and
ravines.
The cunning Ja Katon considered his
options and came up with a plan.
In 1292,
alarming news reached King Kerton's
court.
Messengers would have burst into his
throne room and breathlessly told him
that an army had been seen rampaging
through the farmland to the north,
flying the distinctive white and red
banners of Kadiri.
They had taken the toothless tiger King
Keranagara completely by surprise.
Now, King Jayak Katang set out to
attack. His army coming from the north
consisted of bad people. They were full
of flags and sounds. The area to the
north was devastated.
Dismayed at the destruction, the king
appointed one of his son-in-laws to lead
what forces he had remaining in Java. A
man named Raden Vijaya.
This young man marched north with the
remains of the royal army and met
Jaakatong's rampaging forces in battle.
As one Javanese inscription carved at a
place called Kudadu describes,
when King Jaya Katon's troops reached
the village of Jasun Wong Kal, King
Kerta Nagara sent his son-in-law Raden
Wijaya to fight the enemy. After the
battle, the enemy fled while suffering a
great loss. Seemingly they disappeared
forever.
Raden Vagaya had succeeded in the north
and defended his father-in-law's
kingdom, which he was set to one day
inherit.
But now the true strategy of Jaong was
revealed.
While this loud northern force had been
burning and sacking their way through
the north of the kingdom, a much larger
second force had also advanced in the
south. This army moved much more
stealthily through the ravines and
valleys of the central highlands
as the paraton describes.
Then a large army descended from Kadiri
coming from the banks of the Axa River
heading towards Lour.
They were not allowed to carry flags or
make any noise.
Upon arrival at Sidabana,
they headed straight for Singasari.
be son.
>> This force would go completely unnoticed
and they apparently arrived at the
kingdom's capital of Coutaraja while
King Keranagara was drunk.
Drinking in Java was a serious business
and a large number of alcoholic
beverages were consumed for pleasure,
especially on special occasions.
One Javanese poem known as the Sumana
Santa describes the drinks available at
an idealized wedding.
The drinks poured continuously from rock
crystal pitches like fountains of palm
syrup. Sugar cane, wine, and rice beer
were drunk one after the other like holy
water and meat welling up from glass
vessels.
>> But the influence of tantric Buddhism
meant that drinking was more than just
for fun. In fact, it was at times a
spiritual practice and even a royal
duty.
The king was required to take part in
ceremonies known as chakra puja which
involved the drawing of geometric
designs on the earth with colored powder
after which the ritual could take place.
The historian Miranda Shaw describes the
unfolding of one of these rituals.
An elaborate array of offerings and
foods are laid out. The participants
dawn special insignia like bone
ornaments and crowns and use musical
instruments of archaic design such as
skull drums, thighbone trumpets, and
conch horns for inducing heightened
awareness. Practitioners sit in a circle
and partake of sacramental meat and wine
served in skull cups. The feast
culminates in the performance of tantric
dances and music that must never be
disclosed to outsiders.
While this ceremony was a crucial part
of King Keranagara's royal calendar, the
timing couldn't have been worse.
Jaakatong's concealed force arrived
outside the city walls without warning.
They took the garrison by surprise and
poured over the walls of the city while
the king was thus engaged.
The city was taken and King Keranagaram
was killed.
The king's son-in-law, Raden Vaya, was
still celebrating his victory in the
north, and he must have been distraught
when the news reached him. He had won
his battle, but lost the war, and now
everything he had stood to inherit had
also been taken by the usurper Ja Katon.
Raden Vagaya now retreated to the
rainforests of the northeast and left
the capital and the throne in the hands
of the rebel Ja Katon.
The city of Kusarajjo, the heart of the
Singosari kingdom was looted and
depopulated and many of its people taken
back to Kadiri.
Others simply fled into the safety of
the countryside and never returned.
Some stonemasons working on a new temple
in the city simply dropped their tools
in the middle of carving their reliefs
and never came back to finish them.
After that, the city was left to crumble
and be taken over by the encroaching
forest.
Now the dispossessed prince Raden Vagaya
and the rebel usurper Ja Katon faced off
against one another. But it seems
neither side of this civil war was
confident in victory.
Raden vagaya wasn't strong enough to
march south and take his enemy's capital
of Kadiri.
And meanwhile, Jaakong couldn't leave
his city and risk losing his shaky grasp
on the throne.
Both parties entered into an uneasy
negotiation.
And eventually, the rebel king settled
for buying off Raden Vaga.
In exchange for laying down his arms,
the prince would be granted a piece of
land, and there he would be allowed to
build a city.
Rod and Vaga, now completely out of
other options and stranded in the wild
rainforest, had no choice but to agree.
But it must have been with no small
amount of bitterness.
The prince must have felt bitter too
when he reached the piece of land that
Ja Katang had granted him. It was a wild
overgrown jungle in the middle of a
sparsely inhabited area known as the
Tardic Forest.
But his fate was sealed, and he
swallowed his bitterness and ordered his
people to begin clearing the land for
construction and farming.
The old growth forests of Java were
dense and wild, fed by the volcanic
soil.
Colorful hornvilles roosted in the
treetops, while hidden high among the
branches, gibbons greeted the rising sun
with their long mournful songs.
Troops of long-tailed macac monkeys
leapt through the trees, while sambar
deer crept through the shade of the
forest. Great pythons lay coiled in the
trees, and dangerous animals like the
Javan leopard and wild boar lurked
hidden in the green undergrowth.
Everywhere could be heard the creaking
of cicardas and frogs calling to one
another from hidden pools.
At sunset, fruit bats rose in their
thousands from their hidden caves, while
fireflies would have been visible at
night.
The trees were the most ancient life of
the forest.
Towering hardwoods like teik, ebony, and
tamarind would have risen here,
interspersed with bamboo groves,
strangler figs, palms, and tangled lyana
vines, all competing for every shaft of
sunlight.
But when they began cutting down this
forest, Raden Vaga's men found that a
particular kind of tree grew there in
great quantities.
This was the tree that grows a fruit
which in Indonesia is called maja and is
known elsewhere as a wood apple,
elephant apple or Indian quint.
These maja fruits are pear-shaped and
the size of a large grapefruit with a
thick hard woody rind that needs to be
cracked with a hammer.
Inside is an orangey yellow pulp that
gives off the scent of roses but tastes
sweet and bitter a little like
marmalade.
The word for bitter in Japanese is
parit. And due to the large numbers of
these maja fruits growing in this
region, the people named this place Maja
Parit or Bitter Wood apple as the
Paraton describes.
When the mades were building the
village, a hungry man lacking supplies
while cutting down the forest ate a
marajger fruit. He found it bitter and
threw away all the mara fruit he had
picked. The majger fruit there became
known for its bitter taste and the place
was then named.
abide
>> for Raden Vajaya and his people. The
name Maja Pahit was a perfect
encapsulation of the bitterness of their
situation.
They had lost a kingdom and gained a
plot of wild jungle in return and all
because of the treachery of Ja Katon.
They all must have shared a single
desire to throw out the rebel king and
unite Java once more.
Their chance would come in the year 1293
when the sails of the Mongol fleet
appeared on the horizon.
The Mongol fleet that had been sent to
punish the people of Java was led by a
commander named Sherbi.
When he heard of the death of King
Keranagara, he must have found himself
in a quandry. His emperor demanded
vengeance, and he and his men had sailed
for months to get there. He must have
feared leaving empty-handed.
It was while he was puzzling over this
situation that Sherbi was approached by
a messenger from the bitter lord of the
new city of Majapahit,
the dispossessed prince Raden Vagaya.
The Chinese history of Yuan describes
the deal that the Mongols struck
at that time. and Java carried on an old
feud with the neighboring country and
the old king of Java had already been
killed.
The son-in-law of the former Raden
Vijaya had attacked Jaakaton but could
not overcome him. He therefore retired
to Maja Pahit. And when he heard that
Sheibi and his army had arrived, he sent
envoys with an account of his rivers and
seap ports and a map of the country,
offering his submission and asking for
assistance.
She then advanced with all his forces.
For the Mongols, the arrangement was a
neat way to solve their problem.
They would help Raden Vaga overthrow the
rebel Ja Katang and place him on the
throne as a kind of puppet king,
swearing allegiance to the Mongols in
China.
Then Sherb could return to Kubla Khan
and say that he had brought the defiant
little island back under control.
But among Raden Vajaya's men, it must
have been a controversial proposal.
The Javanese were a proud people, and
few had any desire to be ruled by the
faroff Mongol Emperor.
Some may even have called Raden Vaga a
coward and a traitor.
But all this time he was hatching a plot
of his own.
The later chronicle of the Paraton
describes the ensuing war referring to
the Mongols as Tatas.
The Tata army came out from the north
while the Majapahit armies came out from
the east.
King Jayakong was confused, unsure which
to guard. Then he was attacked heavily
from the north by the Tata army.
King Jay Katang, who was fighting to the
north, armed with a shield, was attacked
together by the Tata people and was
finally caught and imprisoned by the
Tatas.
The Mongols had now become kingmakers in
Java. The 13th century Persian historian
Abdullah Wasaf describes how they put
Radan Vaya on the Javanese throne.
His majesty Kublai put the old king's
son-in-law Vijaya on the steps of the
throne. He bestowed on him a ceremonial
dress of honor and conferred on him much
grace. And in exchange for the payment
of tribute and taxes of pearls and gold,
he left the island in his hands.
The Mongol Emperor Kubli must have been
ecstatic when he heard the news.
Finally, here was a victory he could
show to his people.
The wealthy island of Java would now be
added to his imperial domain along with
its control of major shipping lanes. And
perhaps now the fortunes of his
teetering empire would finally turn
around.
But that was not to be the case.
That's because the new king Raden Vaya
had no intention of ruling Java as a
vassel of Kubla Khan. And the moment he
got to power, he turned on the Mongol
forces who had helped him seize the
throne.
The Chinese history of Yuan gives a tur
account of this disastrous turnaround.
Raden Vagaya asked permission to return
to his country in order to prepare a new
letter of submission to the emperor and
to take the precious articles in his
possession back to court.
Shui consented to this and sent two
officers with 200 men to go with him.
But on the way, Raden Vagaya killed the
two officers and revolted again.
After which he availed himself of the
circumstance that the main army was
returning to attack it from both sides.
The Mongol army believed their mission
to be complete and were already packing
their ships to leave.
The seasonal winds were about to change
direction, and if they didn't move fast,
they might become stranded on Java for
another 6 months.
When Raden Vaga's soldiers burst out of
the forest in ambush, firing arrows and
darts from their blow guns, the Mongol
Yuan troops were taken completely by
surprise.
The Javanese epic poem Bulman Taka
describes a battle of this kind.
They were thrown into disarray and in
fear the demon army fled and many of the
demons and their leaders were struck
dead. They withdrew in haste to the
shelter of the fort but were pursued.
Others shuddering sought a way of
resisting but lacked the strength and
hit by arrows floundered about and all
of them left in fear and ran away. The
whole fort was in uproar and all shouted
in confusion. The fires glowed and
blazed up frightfully like an erupting
volcano.
Thousands were killed and the remains of
the Mongol army fled in disarray back to
the ships as the history of Yuan
describes.
Sheep was left behind and was cut off
from the rest of the army. He was forced
to fight his way back to the ships for a
distance of more than 100 miles. At
last, he embarked again and reached
China on a voyage of 68 days. Of his
soldiers, more than 3,000 men had died.
When news of this betrayal reached the
emperor Kubla Khn, we can only imagine
his rage.
He ordered the general sherb to receive
17 lashes and commanded a third of his
property to be confiscated as punishment
for his failure.
He ordered his ministers to begin
immediate preparations for a fullscale
invasion of Java with an even larger
army of 100,000 men. But these plans
would never come to fruition.
The disaster in Java would be the last
campaign of Kubla Khan's reign and he
died the next year in February of 1294
at the age of 78.
After that, the Mongol Yuan dynasty
would enter into a steady and
irrevocable decline and would collapse
entirely little more than 70 years
later.
One great empire was coming to an end.
But in its collapse, it gave way for the
rise of what was now the undisputed
major power on the island of Java and in
the archipelago of Nusan Tar, the new
power of Maja Parahit
on the 15th day of the month of Kartika,
the 8th month of the Hindu calendar.
Raden Vagaya was crowned king in the
palace of Majapahit.
What had once been a stretch of wild
jungle was now the beating heart of
Java's most powerful kingdom.
The Chinese history of Sun describes the
appearance of the kings of Java. And
from this we might imagine how this new
king looked on the day of his
coronation.
The king has hair in a knot upon the top
of his head. He wears golden bells, a
silk robe, and shoes of leather. He sits
on a square couch and his functionaries
who see him daily salute him three times
on going away. When he goes out, he
rides on an elephant or sits in a
carriage and from 5 to 700 soldiers
follow him. When the people see the
king, they squat down until he has
passed.
Raden vagaya would rule as the king of
Majapahit for 16 years. But his reign
would be a troubled one.
From the earliest days of his rule, he
faced rebellions, many of them from men
who had fought alongside him against Ja
Katang and the Mongols.
Many of these disagreements were sparked
over the question of who would become
the king's Maha party, a powerful and
influential position that combined
elements of a prime minister and head
general and essentially acted as the
king's right hand.
Whatever his skills as a diplomat, it
seems Raden Vagaya struggled to manage
the ambitions of the men who served
under him.
For this reason, he spent much of his
rule putting down rebellions all over
Java.
In an effort to cement the legitimacy of
his new dynasty, he would marry the
remaining three daughters of his dead
father-in-law, Curtenagara, and ensure
that the royal line of succession would
pass entirely through him. But still the
problems persisted and the new kingdom
teetered on the brink of destruction.
When Raden Vagaya died in the year 1309,
he must have hoped that his only son Ja
would set things right.
But due to the apparently deficient
nature of Gygra's character, this would
not be the case.
King Gienegra would rule for nearly 20
years after the death of his father. But
he was a widely disliked character.
So much so that the author of the
chronicle the paraton would give him the
nickname Kala Gt meaning weak villain.
Meanwhile, the Javanese folk tradition
has remembered him by the name Bajang
Ratu or dwarf king, referencing either
his short stature or simply the
uninspiring nature of his rule.
Gienegra faced multiple attempts on his
life and widespread rebellions, even
worse than his fathers. The most serious
of which was led by a man named Kouti.
This uprising became so dangerous that
the king was forced to abandon his
capital for a time. And it's during this
time of upheaval that a man would walk
onto the historical stage who would turn
around the fortunes of this new and
struggling kingdom.
He was a soldier who led the king's
bodyguard during the Couti rebellion and
gained a position of trust in the royal
court.
His name was Gaja Mada.
Gaja Mada's name came from the old
Javanese word gaja meaning elephant and
ma which is a difficult to translate
word describing a state of furious
intoxication.
This probably alluded to the period of a
few weeks every year when male elephants
enter their breeding cycle called must
and their testosterone levels explode.
During this time, a bull elephant seeps
liquid from a gland around its ears and
becomes extremely aggressive and
dangerous.
Elephants had long been used for warfare
in Java. They formed the centerpiece of
any army and allowed royals and generals
to command the battlefield from an
elevated position.
Although prehistoric fossils of native
elephants have been found in Java, this
species had long been extinct by this
point. And during the medieval period,
elephants were imported from other
lands.
They were enormous, expensive, and
prestigious. Their tusks sometimes
adorned with metal implements to make
them even more deadly and their sides
often oiled before going into battle to
prevent the enemy from climbing on their
backs.
So this commander's name would have
generated images of strength, vitality,
and an unstoppable force. and by all
accounts it would be a good fit.
Although the elephant general Gaja Mada
would eventually rise through the new
kingdom of Majapahit to become one of
its most influential statesmen, his
birth was relatively unexceptional.
We know little about his early life, but
he was likely born into a poor family in
the area around the city of Majapi, and
his father was possibly killed in the
war with the Mongols.
But he would prove his worth and become
the head of the king's elite royal
bodyguard, the Bayara.
After successfully protecting the king
through the Kouti rebellion, Gajamada
would be rewarded with the governorship
of a small province.
Finally, he would be named Maha Parti or
the right hand of the king.
The epic poem the Desha Varana describes
this warrior statesman in the following
terms.
Gaja Mada is the excellent party of
Maja, an officer valiant, discerning in
tactics with a firm foundation in
loyalty and devotion to the king.
Eloquent and skilled in speech, polite
and patient, constantly exerting
himself, unremitting, he watches over
the king's position as supreme ruler of
the world.
King Jane was clearly a man ills suited
to rule. But with Gaja Mada's help, he
was able to keep hold of his kingdom by
his fingernails. And it's in the last
decade of his reign that a visitor from
a far off land arrived on the shores of
Java.
He was a traveler from the northern
Italian region of Friulia, then a
territory of the Holy Roman Empire. And
his name was Odorich of Pordinon.
Around the year 1318,
Odorich had departed from Venice and
spent the next decade or so traveling
all over Asia, passing through Persia
and seeing the ruins of the ancient city
of Percepilus.
He then sailed through the strait of
Hormuz to India and from there through
the straits of Malaca to Borneo, Sumatra
and Java.
When he returned home, he dictated the
memoirs of his travels in a work
entitled the relatio de miraabilus
oriental tatarorum or the account of the
marvels of the eastern tartas.
In this text he provides a remarkable
snapshot of life in Java around the year
1320.
There is an island which is called Java
which is a good 3,000 mi around. The
king of this island has under him seven
crowned kings as vassels. This island is
very populous and is the second best of
all islands that be on the earth. One
finds there cloves, pepper, nutmeg, and
many other precious spices that they
grind there and all manner of
necessities in great quantity.
Odric was particularly impressed by the
royal palace of Geneagra which was
richly decorated in gold mined from the
volcanic mountain ranges.
The king of this island lives in a
marvelous and very large palace. Its
steps are of gold and silver
alternately.
The paving tiles are likewise one gold
and the next silver. The walls are
covered with plates of gold and there
are mounted men sculpted out of gold on
them with golden circles around their
heads like the diadems we make for the
figures of saints. And these circles are
full of precious stones. To put it
briefly, this is the richest and
loveliest palace that there be in the
whole world.
Odorich also records that many still
remembered the war with the Mongol Yuan
dynasty of China now nearly 30 years in
the past.
The great Khn of Cath who is the
sovereign emperor of all the Tartas has
often made war with this king and often
brought battle to him. But this king has
always defeated him.
But despite the glowing report of
Odorich and the ongoing help of the
elephant general Gaja Mada, Jay Negra's
reign was a poor one.
He was so insecure in his rule that he
at one point seems to have considered
marrying two of his own sisters named
Diar Wyatt and Diar Gitar to ensure that
no rivals could arise from the royal
line.
When opposition to this plan exploded in
the court and their mother loudly
protested, King Jane gave up on this
idea. But he still forbade his sisters
from marrying anyone else.
King Genegra had two sisters born of the
same mother.
He did not permit them to be married to
others, wishing to keep them for
himself.
Therefore, no prince dared remain openly
at Majapahit.
Any man who appeared was driven away,
lest he seek their hands, and the other
nobles kept themselves hidden in fear.
The
>> Genegra confined these two princesses
for years in the women's quarters of the
palace and prevented anyone from seeing
them.
It was a microcosm of a rule that seems
to have been at every turn paranoid,
petty, and authoritarian.
Over the course of his reign, the
kingdom of Majapahit would falter.
The island of Bali, just a short hop
over the Sunda Strait, slipped out of
his control around this time. And people
must have feared that the whole kingdom
would now disintegrate and the land
would return to destructive civil war.
But that was not to be the case.
That's because of a woman who had made
her name standing up to King Gygra,
the mother of the two imprisoned
princesses.
A woman named Dia Guyatry.
>> Diar was a title that in old Javanese
was given to princes and princesses of
the royal line. And diaratri had been
the youngest daughter of king
kertonagara the last king of singari.
She had also been the most senior wife
of the founder of Majaet Raden Vagaya
and all her life she had been a quiet
force behind the lives of these great
men.
As a girl, she had watched her father
brand the face of the Mongol envoys and
then saw her home of Singer Sari
destroyed by the rebellion of Ja Katang.
She had fled through the rice fields to
safety while her home burned behind her.
As a young woman, she had watched the
war with the Mongols unfold, then seen
her husband found the kingdom of
Majapahit, which now stood as his
lasting legacy.
By now, she was a widow in her 50s and
had retired to become a Buddhist nun in
a forest monastery on the slope of a
nearby mountain. But she was still known
by the title Raja Putney, a word which
means wife of kings and which gave her
the prestige of a royal matriarch.
The bumbling king Gienegra was her late
husband's son by another less senior
wife. And we can only imagine how Diar
Guyatri felt now watching from her
monastery as he veered the empire from
crisis to crisis and kept her two
daughters under lock and key.
She must have feared that the legacy
that she and Raden Vaga had built was
about to be destroyed.
But she refused to let that happen.
to help her free her daughters, reclaim
the kingdom, and put it back on course.
This royal matriarch would enlist the
help of the man who had recently been
rising in prominence in the kingdom of
Majapet.
The raging elephant who had become
indispensable to the feckless king.
The soldier and statesman who went by
the name Gaja Mada.
In the year 1328,
it seems they took their chance.
According
to the official story related in the
royal chronicle, the paraton, that year,
King Gienegra was suffering from an
unpleasant condition, a painful boil or
swelling of some kind. And when he
summoned his doctor, a man named Tanka,
he apparently forgot that he had
previously insulted or taken advantage
of this man's wife.
Enraged at this, the doctor Tanka took
his revenge. As the paraton records,
Tanka's wife spread word that the king
had treated her dishonorably.
Tanka was summoned before Gaja.
At that time, King Genegra was suffering
from a swelling and could not leave his
chambers.
Tanka was ordered to perform an
operation with a sharp lancet and he
approached beside the royal bed.
Tanka stabbed the king's boil once, then
again with the blade, but the weapon
would not burst it for the king wore
around his neck an amulet of protection.
Then the king was asked to set this
aside.
He took off the charm and laid it beside
the bed.
Tanka stabbed him again and this time
the blade burst the boil,
but Tanka continued stabbing him and he
did not stop until the king died there
upon the bed.
The doctor turned assassin Tanka was
swiftly killed by Gaja Mada which meant
perhaps conveniently that his side of
the story could never be told.
As historians, we can never actually
know what happened in that room. But the
slightly fanciful story involving a
magical amulet and a vengeful doctor has
left many historians wondering if the
true story wasn't a simpler one that
Gajamada and the Daaja queen Dariatry
had simply plotted together to kill the
king framing the poor doctor.
Whether they had planned the whole thing
or just seized the opportunity on a
stroke of good luck, Gajamada and the
Daaja matriarch Diaratri
went on to seize control of the kingdom.
And it seems King Genegra was
sufficiently disliked that few people
were all that concerned about what might
actually have happened to him.
But the royal matriarch and the general
prime minister faced a problem.
Gaja Mada himself had risen from humble
beginnings. And as a commoner, he had
absolutely no legitimacy to rule under
Javanese law. And while Dioratri was
officially the next in line to the
throne, she had already taken a vow to
become a Buddhist nun, a position that
prevented her from holding any positions
of earthly power.
And she had no sons who might take the
throne.
In fact, the histories record that she
had only given birth to her two
daughters
who were now allowed to leave the palace
for the first time in years.
The Desha Varana describes these women
in conventionally poetic terms.
And then the king giant Nagara was left
behind as king of Maja with his
princesses his youngest sisters who were
the daughters of the worthy Raja Patney
the incomparable.
They were both of the greatest beauty
surpassing the women of heaven. The
elder was princess of Jana and the
younger ruled as princess of Da.
The Raja
soon appointed her young daughter Diar
Git to rule as queen in her place.
Verily in the shaka year moon arrows two
form the princess of jwana succeeded in
maja pahit as queen. It was the
disposition of the great raja patney
that she should be the auspicious leader
of the world distinguished from others.
It was she who made her ruler and
watched over all her affairs.
The princess soon took to the throne and
with her mother watching over her, she
would be a far more capable ruler than
her feckless brother.
She would take a royal name that meant
the exalted goddess of the three worlds
who the glory of Vishnu radiates.
Tribuana vija tuna
tribuana was her mother's daughter. She
was a natural stateswoman and was able
to stabilize the kingdom after the
period of poor leadership that had
preceded her.
and she seems to have learned from the
mistakes of both her father and brother.
Early in her reign, she faced a
rebellion by two men named Sardang and
Keta, and a conflict arose in her court
over which of her generals would lead
her army into battle.
These kinds of political disputes had
plagued the last two kings, but Tribuana
resolved it in a simple way.
Rather than show favor to one general
over the other, she simply led the army
herself. As the desana describes
in Shaka fire's arrow sons, their
enemies were destroyed. Sadeng and Kita
were defeated, overcome by her personal
retinue. Further in the Shaka year,
arrows, seasons, eyes, naval. The king
of Bali was evil and base. He was
attacked with an army, broken and
completely crushed. Every kind of
evildoer was fearful and made off
quickly.
Tribuana's early successes on the
battlefield gave her a taste for
conquest.
And over her rule, this queen of Java
would embark on a massive expansion of
Majapahit
to spread its influence all over the
archipelago.
To embark on this mission, she appointed
as her Maha Party or prime minister the
general who had done more than perhaps
anyone else to keep the young kingdom
together and who had worked with her
mother to depose the previous king.
This was the rampaging elephant himself,
Gaja Mada.
By all accounts, Gajamada rose to this
challenge.
Spurred on by his warlike queen, the
Paraton records him swearing a
remarkable oath of conquest before the
entire royal court.
Gaja Mada swore, "Until I have conquered
the entire Nusantara archipelago, I will
eat no spices nor take any rest. If I
have conquered the Gorum Islands and the
island of Saram, the kingdom of Tanjang
Pura, the kingdoms of Haru and Pahang,
the Don Pu regency, the island of Bali,
the lands of Sunda along with the Tumi
and Palem Bang of Sumatra. Then and only
then will I eat spices and take my rest.
Over
the next three decades, Gaja would lead
the armies of Majapit across the seas
and would bring ever more lands under
the influence and control of the empire.
The Italian traveler Ludovviko Deva
describes the weapons of the Javanese
that he saw when he visited sometime
later around 1505.
They carry bows and the greater part
darts of cane. Some also use blowpipes
with which they throw poison darts and
they throw them with the mouth and
however little they draw blood, the
wounded person dies.
The 12th century Javanese poem, the
Bulman Taka, describes an idealized army
marching to battle and gives a sense for
what it would have been like to see the
forces of Gajamada landing on the shores
of each island in turn and preparing for
war.
Their weapons were spears and lances,
and there were also thousands of bows.
Then came the riding elephants, and
their weapons were spears, lances,
javelins, and clubs. Many heroes were
mounted on horses. Skilled riders in
horseback combat. The spears and very
sharp knives when worldled glowed
brightly. Men came bearing lances and
shields, and others with slingshots.
Their casings shone, wrapped in silk and
gilded, and their various jackets were
like clouds traveling over the earth.
The Majapet forces of Queen Tribuana
Vijay Tungadevi crossed the sea to the
east and reconquered the small island of
Bali in 1343.
After that they went northwest and
absorbed most of the coastal regions of
the larger island of Sumatra into her
growing empire.
Other kingdoms were incorporated
peacefully into the empire as tributary
subjects such as the large island of
Sulai whose name means iron island on
account of the high quality iron it
produced and exported around the region.
The later poem, the Desha Varna, lists
at length all of the island territories
that were either conquered by Maja Pahit
or agreed to pay it tribute without a
fight.
The islands and lesser islands in the
first place coming under the territory
of the Malay islands are Jambi and
Palamang, Keritang, Tiba and Dharmasa.
Following Candice, Kawas, Manang, Kabwa,
Sak, Rekan, Campa and Pane, Campe, Haru
and Mandahiling, Tumihang, Pac and
Barat, Luas and Samudra, as well as
Lamuri, Batan, Lampong and Barus. Those
are the main ones among the Malay
islands. All these countries are subject
and obedient.
The great queen Tribuana Vijay Tungadevi
would rule for 22 years and her reign
saw the rise of Majapay to a true
or an empire of the sea.
But she must have known that her reign
couldn't last forever.
In 1350, her mother, the great royal
matriarch Diar Guyry died, most likely
in her forest monastery after a long and
accomplished life. Her daughter Tribuana
had been ruling ostensibly on behalf of
her mother, and it seems that once the
old woman died, her situation would also
become untenable.
But luckily, by this time she had had a
son who was now the first in the royal
line, and he had just come of age at 16
years old. His name was Hyam Wuruk.
When this young prince Hayam Wuruk came
to the throne, he would have been
crowned with enormous ceremony and
celebration.
The historian Herald Vanderinda
describes the rituals associated with a
Javanese coronation.
At sunset on the eve of the first day of
the first month of the year, priests
entered the inner pavilion of the royal
palace followed by acolytes chanting
sacred Sanskrit texts. King Haim Wuruk
sat on a throne in the amazing pavilion
where mattedhaired rishi hermits and
religious leaders sprinkled holy water
over him to wash away the evils of the
past. As darkness descended, oil lamps
were lit around the palace. A
spectacular sight.
At the striking of a gong, Gaja Mada led
the senior ministers to a large pavilion
in front of the palace gates before a
growing crowd.
Hayamuruk was a multi-talented king.
He was apparently an accomplished singer
and dancer and a lover of shadow puppet
plays.
The poet of the Desha Wanana describes
the auspicious omens that took place
upon the birth of this prince as the
island's great volcanoes rumbled their
approval.
At his birth in the Shaki year, season's
arrow sons, the prince was already
destined to be king.
The signs of his miraculous and
extraordinary nature were that the earth
quaked and rumbled. There was a rain of
ash. Thunder and lightning zigzagged
through the sky. Mount Kampud erupted
and the wretched evildoers around it
were annihilated and died without a
gasp. Such is the nature of his reign
that the whole of the land of Java has
been humbled and bows down in
submission.
Like her mother before her, Tribuana did
not completely vanish from political
life when she stepped away from her
throne.
Throughout the rest of her life, she
would act as a counselor and advisor for
her son, and together they would usher
in what is widely regarded as the golden
age of the empire of Majapet.
When Hyam Wooduk came to the throne, he
inherited a capital city of no little
magnificence.
Over the preceding decades, it had been
the site of constant construction and
now bloomed with palaces and temples
complete with pillared audience halls
and pavilions.
In this era, all roads led to Majapahit
and its status as a crossroads of Java
wasn't just a metaphor.
The epic poem Desa Vanana describes the
royal palace.
Let us describe the layout of the all
inspiring royal palace. Its wall is of
red brick. It goes right around and is
thick and high. On the western side, the
palace mouth faces onto the great square
in the midst of deep encircling with
booty trees in rows and neatly shaped,
all thick with festoons. On the north is
the ceremonial gate, splendid and
extraordinary. Its doors of iron adorned
with countless designs. To the south of
this is the crossroads, otherworldly in
its elegance.
From these crossroads, great highways
snaked off into the country in all
directions.
It was part of the usual ceremony of
kingship that the king of Majapahit
would routinely make journeys around the
whole of Java, meeting his citizens and
seeing the sites of the land, visiting
villages, holy shrines, and reminding
vassal kingdoms about who was in charge.
It was on one of these journeys that
King Hayam Wuruk brought his court poet,
a man named Propanka who would go on to
be the author of the poem Desavanana.
Propanka speaks of the honor in his poem
describing himself in the third person.
In the Shaka moon snake son in the month
of Badra Pada at the fullness of the
moon, King Hayamuruk went on a journey
to Lama to take note of all there was to
see. All the princes of Java with their
wives again went with the king with
servants and vehicles. Officials and
officers from the whole of Majapahit and
in particular the king's priests and
court poets accompanied him. So this man
by the pen name of Propanka joined in
the pursuit of beauty attending at the
feet of the king.
According to his own account, Propanka
seems to have embarked on writing the
desana because he felt unable to write
the kind of poetry that the more senior
court poets were producing.
usually heroic epics about the Hindu
gods as he describes in the following
extract.
His motive was after all to follow the
king wherever he went in the hope of
being favored. But he still does not
know how to achieve poetic effects and
is most unlikely to succeed in composing
a song on the writing tablet. And this
is the reason why he describes all the
places passed through and sets out their
names in order along the road.
Ironically, the Dash of Varna is today
one of the most famous pieces of
literature to survive from the Javanese
golden era and it is by far the most
useful to historians.
Today, the poem is a remarkable source
that captures a snapshot of life on Java
during the reign of Hyam Wuruk. And for
all of this, we have the poet Propanka's
apparent inferiority complex to thank.
Along their journey, Propanka watched
the king carefully and noted down the
beauty of the land they passed through.
At Dampar and at Patanjungan, the king
relaxed and made his way along the
beach. To the east his path followed the
level sands, which was so firm that the
carriages could drive over them. He made
a halt on the banks of a lake thick with
white and red lotuses in flour, and was
absorbed in watching the giant shrimps
moving about in the limpid water,
clearly visible in the depths.
But the royal journey wasn't always an
easy one.
In his text, we get a sense for the
challenges of moving over land during
the rainy season.
>> The road just at the point where it runs
northward from the sea over its whole
length was rough and narrow. On top of
this, it rained so that the steep places
became slippery and some of the
carriages came loose and collided with
each other.
Due to these challenges, travel by road
was largely only possible during the dry
season. For the rest of the year, goods
were transported by river, taking rice
and other export crops downstream to the
great port cities on barges.
These boats would then sail back up the
rivers with luxury goods imported from
China, India, and elsewhere.
These port cities were the beating heart
of the Majapahit Empire. And the large
numbers of Chinese coins found in their
archaeological sites testify to the
booming trade that went on.
At each of these ports, the sales of
hundreds of ships would be visible,
coming and going with countless trade
goods. And among these, the most
lucrative were the spices grown on the
islands of the archipelago that were
prized all around the world, such as
pepper, cardamom, and ginger.
But the rarest of all were cloves and
nutmeg.
Cloves and nutmeg were brought to
Majapahit on large ships that sailed
from a small group of islands which are
called the islands of Maluku and would
come to be known as the spice islands.
While cloves were grown all over these
islands, nutmeg was extremely limited in
cultivation,
occurring only on 10 islands in the tiny
archipelago of Banda.
Wild nutmeg had long been harvested by
the peoples native to the Bander
Islands, but it was a particularly
difficult plant to cultivate.
Nutmeg seeds will fail to germinate if
they aren't planted in soil within a
week, making them difficult to transport
by sea. And the particular environment
of volcanic soil that they evolved in
means that they are fragile and
difficult to nurture to full size.
As a result of these difficulties, the
Bander Islanders claimed that nutmeg was
simply a gift of the gods and could not
be cultivated by human hands.
Instead, they would travel to the parts
of the forest where it grew wild to
collect its prized seeds. And they kept
the location of these groves a carefully
guarded secret.
But despite its extreme rarity, the
fragrant nutmeg seeds that these
islanders harvested traveled all around
the world.
The spice would reach Constantinople in
the sixth century and instantly became a
sought after commodity and mark of
luxury.
Nutmeg would even be mentioned as a
spice to flavor English ale in Chaucer's
Canterbury Tales, which was written
during the time of the Majapahit Empire.
At times, nutmeg would sell on the other
side of the world for more than an
equivalent weight of gold.
As a result of this global trade, the
rulers of the Bander Islands would come
to be known around the region as the
Orurang Kaya or rich men. And the
entirety of this trade passed through
the major ports of Majapahit.
To transport these goods across the seas
and oceans, the sailors of Majapahit
voyaged in large vessels known as Jongs.
These were the descendants of the Bora
Budor ships that had sailed to
Madagascar and Eastern Africa in the
preceding centuries.
And by this time, some of these ships
had reportedly grown to phenomenal
proportions.
Reports on the true size of these
vessels vary, but some sources record
jongs that reached a size of 80 m long.
They were built with layered hulls that
made them exceptionally strong and were
able to transport a thousand soldiers
and more than a,000 tons of cargo.
The sight of these massive jongs
astonished European explorers when they
arrived in the archipelago in the 16th
century.
One Portuguese admiral and explorer
Alphonso de Alba wrote about
encountering one of these enormous
vessels in 1511.
The whole fre went back along the coast
in the same order as they had first
come. And when they were in the latitude
of the powder island, they cighted two
very large junks and gave chase to them.
One of these, which was from India,
surrendered immediately. But the other
junk would not do so.
The Portuguese gave chase to the massive
Javanese ship and made several attempts
to board it, but these were all
unsuccessful.
The Europeans even opened fire on the
Jong with their cannons, but found that
the three or four layers of wood with
which the Javanese built their ships
simply absorbed the cannon fire and the
vast vessel sailed on.
In a letter written sometime later, one
of the Portuguese captains, Ferno Perez
de Andrada, describes the massive
Javanese ship.
The junk was the largest seen by men of
these parts so far. It carried a
thousand fighting men on board. And your
lordship can believe me that it was an
amazing thing to see because beside it,
our own vessel, the Anuniada, did not
look like a ship at all. We attacked it
with bombards, but even the shots of the
largest cannon did not pierce it below
the waterline.
It was so monstrous that no man had ever
seen the like.
Eventually, the smaller and more
maneuverable Portuguese ships were able
to disable the larger Jong by breaking
its two massive rudders.
This finally brought the men on board to
surrender.
The Europeans were so impressed with the
size of these Javanese Jongs that they
sailed one of them all the way back home
where it was used for a time as a
warship in the fleet guarding the
Gibralta Strait.
Although we have little reliable data on
when the ships of the Javanese reached
such a massive scale, it is reasonable
to assume that they were at least
approaching that size during the reign
of Hyam Wuruk when the power of
Majapahit was at its peak.
These enormous ships would have been the
crucial backbone of the Majapahit Empire
with their enormous capacity for cargo
and their ability to transport thousands
of men, horses, and even elephants from
island to island wherever they were
needed.
And of course they would have made a
powerful statement about the power and
prestige of the empire of Majapahit.
By now, the Majapahit sphere of
influence stretched over the sea for
thousands of kilometers, and they had
monopolized the lucrative spice routes
from the Malaku Islands so that their
wealth would have swelled to previously
unimagined heights.
Over this period, Majapahit began to
take on the form of what has been called
a Mandala Empire.
In Sanskrit, the word mandala means
circle and it has come to describe a
style of traditional geometric pattern
used to represent a kind of map of the
universe
reflected in the shapes of the Buddhist
temples at Seu and Borau Budur. These
are designed to help an adherent achieve
a state of meditation.
Although the forms of these mandalas
differ, many show the sacred mountain
meu at the center of the world,
sometimes surrounded by the world ocean.
Around this is a square palace with four
gates and then a circle representing the
continents outside it. The heavens and
the world of the gods forming the
outside of the pattern.
The mandala presents the vision of a
world ordered in a strict hierarchy
radiating out from the center. And so
it's no surprise it has long been used
as a way of visualizing royal power.
As early as the 4th century BC, the
Indian writer Killilia in his work the
Arth Shastra described what he called
the Raja Mandala or Mandala of kings in
which a powerful ruler will bring other
less powerful ones under his control.
This idea has become popular among
modern historians seeking to understand
how Southeast Asian states of this time
were organized and there's some evidence
that this is also how the Javanese of
the time would have thought of their
world.
The epic poem the desavan describes the
structure of the Majapayah Empire like
the solar system with power radiating
out from the center like the rays of the
sun.
The royal compound at Maja the
incomparable is as sun and the moon and
the courtyards of the many quarters each
with its own particular charm are rays
of light in relation to it. Like the
stars and planets are the various
remaining cities. Daha the foremost and
the other islands and all the
surrounding countries which seek refuge
and in numbers come into the presence.
It's still an open question exactly how
much power Majapahit exerted over its
vassal states.
Some empires like the Roman Empire ruled
with direct control.
When they conquered a new area, they
erased previous forms of government and
social structures. and imposed their own
on absorbed territories.
But we don't see much evidence of that
in the case of Majapahit.
Subordinate kings and rulers on the
outer islands certainly paid symbolic
homage to the king in Majapah.
They likely provided an agreed upon
tribute each year and a certain number
of soldiers and ships for any military
action undertaken by the empire.
But beyond that, it's likely that the
lords of each island and tributary
kingdom continued to exert more or less
total control over their own affairs.
This arrangement suited everyone well.
Cultural identities on each individual
island were relatively distinct and
deeply entrenched.
Local languages and customs were
different on each island, and few people
around the region wanted to be directly
ruled by a Javanese governor or to have
Javanese troops stationed in their
hometowns.
And for the Majapayah, appointing
governors and stationing troops to put
down rebellions and uprisings would have
been an unwelcome expense.
The Mandala structure was cheap and
efficient.
While times were good and the empire was
strong, it ensured a maximum level of
compliance and cooperation from subjects
with the lightest possible touch and
allowed everyone to profit from the
great traffic of trade that flowed along
the great arteries of the sea.
From the center of the mandala in
Majapahit, fleets of Jong ships sailed
back and forth among the islands,
bringing trade and tribute back to its
booming ports.
But as with any empire, sometimes its
subjects had to be kept in line, as the
Deshavan describes.
The other countries, all that were under
the care of Java, obeyed the king's
commands, and each was true in what it
did. Furthermore, any that transgressed
his commands was attacked and wiped out
completely by the squadrons of the
various valiant naval officers.
One such example occurred in the year
when one of the subject kings of the
empire seemed to get ideas above his
station.
The troublesome king in question was a
man named Aditya Vamman who had been put
in power by Majapahit on the large
island of Sumatra, a short hop over the
sea from Java.
Aditioan was something of a narcissist.
He was fond of commissioning massive
statues of himself, larger than any that
have been uncovered of other kings in
the region, and over the preceding years
he had begun to act in an insubordinate
manner.
At one point, he had a stone tablet
inscribed that showed a list of kings,
and he had the insulence to place his
own name above King Hyam Woods.
This all would have caused rumbles of
constonnation at the court of Majapahed.
But Aditio would go too far when he sent
his own envoys to the court of the
emperor of China, bypassing his king
completely.
One Javanese epic poem, the Parata Yuda,
describes the rage of the demon king
Ravena, upon getting news of the death
of his sons. But we might imagine it a
fitting description of Hayam Wuruk's
reaction when he heard that Aditya had
been going over his head and making
overtures to China without consulting
him.
The monarch was furiously enraged. He
gnored his mustaches, his countenance
was inflamed, and his bosom red as the
waari flower. Sweat exuded from every
paw. The angles of his mouth trembled.
His eyelashes stuck together. He
vaunted. He called aloud. He challenged
all his enemies to meet him at once.
Hayam Wuruk summoned the Chinese
ambassador to Sumatra and after
lambasting him apparently had the man
beheaded and his head sent back to China
in a bag.
In perhaps a sign of the power of
Majapahit at this time the Chinese
didn't respond in kind.
Instead, they bashfully apologized for
their mistake and would eventually send
a gift of fine fabrics and a batch of
paper money to the Javanese court to
make amends.
But from the vain king Aditioan,
no apology would suffice.
King Hayam Wuruk amassed his army, as
many as 300 warships and according to
the chronicles, 200,000 soldiers to
crush this upstart king.
And although we don't hear what happened
to him, Aditioan never appears in any
other written records or inscriptions
again.
Now Hayam Wuruk was on the war path.
After crushing Aditioan, the Majapahit
fleet rounded on another problematic
vassel.
This man ruled the walled settlement of
Singapura, now the modern city of
Singapore, and his name was Paramevara.
After a month-long siege, the Majapahed
forces broke through the walls and
slaughtered the inhabitants.
To this day, legend has it that the
ironrich reddish clay soil of Singapore
was stained that color by the blood
spilled during this massacre.
Paramea, the king of Singapura, fled
north to the area of the Malaca Strait,
but he would remain a thorn in the side
of Majapah for some time to come.
The Aditia incident shows that the
empire of Majapahit was held together by
trade and diplomacy and the promise of
mutual peace and prosperity.
But it was also very much backed by the
threat of force.
Over this period, the royal capital
would flourish.
But this golden age of Majapahit could
not last forever and its end would come
about after the death of its last great
king Hayam Wuruk.
King Hayam Wuruk died likely in the year
and with him the light began to leave
the court of Majapah.
The great statesman and general Gajamada
had died 25 years earlier and Hayam
Wuruk's mother queen Tribuana Vijay
Tungadevi had also died a decade or so
after that.
There now seems to have been something
of a vacuum of talent in the Majapahit
court.
Exacerbating the problem was the
complexity of Javanese succession laws
which had developed to deal with the
fact that kings of this time always had
multiple wives.
In ideal circumstances, the law would
unambiguously favor one successor over
another, and there would be no confusion
about who would take the throne.
But fate had dealt Hyamuruk a bad hand
when it came to his succession.
He had failed to have a son by his
principal wife and so his closest legal
heir was therefore a woman named Kusumov
Vardini, his daughter by a lower ranking
wife.
She had married a man named Vikramordina
and so it seemed likely that he would
become king despite having only married
into the royal family.
The Dashaner describes this couple in
glowing terms.
>> They have as daughter Princess Kusuma
Wadani, a blameless young princess who's
paid homage in the royal compound of
Cabalan and is of the utmost charm.
Prince Wikramama Wadana will be her
proper match as everyone says they will
be like a god and goddess when they
marry later, bringing happiness to
people's hearts.
But Hayam Wuruk did also have a son by a
secondary less senior wife.
In the histories, he is known only by
the title Bra Vabumi or the lord of a
place called Virumi.
Being a man and the direct descendant of
Hyam Wuruk also gave him a strong claim
to the throne despite his mother being
of a lower rank than Kusumo Vines.
And this situation of two people having
a comparable claim was a recipe for
disaster.
Hyam Muruk seems to have sensed the
danger while he was still alive.
In an attempt to remedy the situation
and cool off the rivalry between these
two men, he divided the empire into the
western court, the capital of Majapet,
and the eastern court, where the lord of
Virumi held sway.
The exact details of this arrangement
are unknown, but it was a clear and
obvious rift, now splitting the
kingdom's Javanese heartlands in two.
The situation seems to have gotten so
bad that at one point the Chinese
chronicle, the Ming Shilu, notes that
the two different courts were each
sending their envoys to meet
independently with the emperor's
ambassadors.
Like the rumblings and earthquakes
before a great eruption, the signs of
trouble must have been obvious to anyone
who was paying attention.
And in the years that followed, the rift
would tear apart the land of Java and
the empire it ruled.
The name for the conflicts that follows
is found in the chronicle of the
Paraton.
There it is called the regreg, a word
that in Javanese means bit by bit and
can be used to describe something
falling apart piece by piece.
As we will see, this was a fitting name
as the conflict would bring about the
steady coming apart of the Mandala
Empire of Majapet
that had held together over the last
century.
The paraton describes the conflict that
unfolded.
>> They came to blows. There was division
and men died in the division.
After 3 years, there then arose again
the regreg war. Both sides prepared
themselves. All the lords asked
themselves, "Whom shall I follow?"
Then the fighting began.
The regreg war would rage for 2 years
and over this time neither side could
gain the upper hand.
The para raton describes the back and
forth nature of the fighting.
First the western palace was defeated.
Their lords were hardpressed.
In distress they wished to flee. Then
they said, "Do not flee yet. Let us
fight them." Then the eastern palace was
defeated.
The strength of the Mandala Empire
system was in how light a hold it
exerted on its vassels.
It was a cheap and efficient way to run
an imperial system. But this strength in
times of stability became a weakness
when times got hard.
For the kings who swore allegiance to
Majapay, it was all too easy when the
empire was distracted to simply turn
away and quietly stop paying its fees or
sending it troops.
With the power of Majapahit's fleet and
army now focused entirely on the war
between its western and eastern courts,
many of its formerly most loyal subjects
simply slipped out of its grasp.
One of these subjects was in the region
of Malayu, which during the Regreg War
drifted under the sovereignty of the
powerful kingdom of Aayutaya in what is
now Thailand.
On the island of Sumatra, a Chinese
pirate named Chen Zooi from Guangdong
even took advantage of the chaos caused
by the regreg war to seize control of
the wealthy port city of Palumbang.
This man would run Palumbang as a pirate
fortress for the better part of a
decade, using it as a base to raid the
wealthy shipping that passed through the
Malaca Strait and using forged bronze
seals to create counterfeit licenses and
aid smuggling into and out of China.
The Chinese Muslim writer Mahan wrote
about the situation in his work, A
Survey of the Ocean Shores.
Chanzui plundered ships and prayed on
both native and foreign merchants for
several years.
On the northern coast of Borneo, the
Brune Kingdom had also begun to ignore
the overlordship of Majapah.
And by 1405, Western Borneo had also
drifted away.
These small kingdoms would instead seek
protection under the influence of
another power that was now flexing its
muscles with increasing confidence on
the waves.
That was the rising Ming dynasty of
China.
By this time, the Mongol Yuan dynasty
had collapsed and the Mongols had been
forcibly thrown out of China. Now, a new
dynasty known as the Ming had taken its
place.
The Ming ruled over a devastated land
that had suffered immensely over the
years of Mongol conquest and misrule by
the Yuan emperors, exacerbated by the
ravages of the Black Death.
But now, China was rebuilding.
Ultimately, the Ming Dynasty has been
remembered as a paranoid and
inward-looking state, which virtually
bankrupted itself with the construction
of its vast Great Wall in the north,
sealing itself off from the world.
But at the start of the 15th century,
Ming China looked quite different.
This was partly due to the reign of an
ambitious and outward-looking ruler
known as the Yong Lur Emperor.
The Yonglur emperor was a patron of
learning and sponsored the writing of a
great encyclopedia made up of 23,000
written scrolls in an attempt to record
all the world's knowledge.
He was fascinated by everything and
especially the world outside of China as
he recorded in his work Ming Taong Baoun
or the valuable teachings of Emperor
Yong Lur.
Whenever I can find the time, I read
history books and the classics so as to
avoid idol living. I constantly remind
myself that the world is so vast and
state affairs so important that I cannot
succumb to laziness and complacency for
even a moment. Once one has succumbed to
laziness and complacency,
everything will become stagnant.
As a result of this fascination with the
outer world, throughout his reign, he
sent out a flurry of diplomatic missions
to all corners of Asia, letting everyone
know that China was once again open for
business. And as part of this effort, he
ordered the construction of a grand
fleet designed to sail around the region
and remind the people of every land of
the might of China.
To build his fleet, the Yonglur Emperor
ordered the construction of a vast
shipyard at a place called Liang or
Dragon River.
This sprawling industrial complex was
built at the point where the Yangti
River is met by the smaller Chin Wai in
the Ming capital of Nanjing.
And it would be the largest shipyard
anywhere in the world.
On its seven long large docks, at least
100 ships could be built at any one
time.
To help in his mammoth effort, the
Yonglur emperor invited more than 20,000
craftsmen to work here on his ships. And
timbers of elm, cedar, and campfor were
brought in enormous quantities to the
city of Nanjing, transported from inland
ports down the rivers on flatbottomed
barges.
The noise of the shipwrights shouting
and calling. The thump of the massive
beams being lifted into place. The
beating of chisels and hammers on nails.
All of this would have sounded over the
rooftops of Nanjing in the early years
of the 15th century. For China, it was
the sound of industry and progress. But
for the power of Majapahit far across
the sea in the south, it might as well
have been the sound of nails being
driven into its coffin.
By the year 1405, as the regreg civil
war dragged on in Majapay, the Yonglur
emperor had completed his grand fleet.
And now all he needed was an admiral to
lead it.
The man he chose was a unic, a giant
named Jungh.
In some ways, Jungha was an unlikely
candidate to become China's most famous
sailor and admiral.
For one thing, he had barely any sailing
experience.
But he had spent much of his life
serving the Yonglur Emperor as a
military commander and had proved
himself a capable and loyal general.
Jungha was a Muslim born into a devout
family in the southwest of China, but he
had been captured during the wars of the
preceding decades and had been castrated
and brought up a unic as a kind of
military slave.
One writer named Yuan Jong describes his
towering stature with perhaps some
exaggeration.
He was 7 ft tall and had a waist about 5
ft in circumference. His cheeks and
forehead were high, but his nose was
small. He had glaring eyes, teeth as
white and well-shaped as shells, and a
voice as loud as a huge bell. He knew a
great deal about warfare, and was well
accustomed to battle.
On the 11th of July 1405, under the
command of Admiral Jung Ha, this vast
fleet set sail
and it would have made an awe inspiring
site.
It comprised a total of 317
vessels of the latest design, including
at least 60 vast treasure ships that
were among the largest in the world.
By some sources, these could have
measured more than 120 m in length and
50 in breadth, making them still among
the largest wooden sailing ships built
anywhere in the world.
These vessels were each fitted with 24
cast bronze cannons and were beautifully
decorated too with their prows carved
with animal heads, dragons, phoenixes
and eagles all painted in bright colors.
Like the ancient Greeks, Egyptians,
Phoenicians, and Romans, the Chinese
painted eyes on the fronts of their
vessels so that the ships seemed to take
on a life of their own and see their way
through mists and stormy seas.
On board these hundreds of ships were a
total of 28,000 men, including sailors
and soldiers, but also diplomats,
astronomers, linguists, interpreters,
and doctors, as well as carpenters, and
ship builders for if the vessels needed
repairing while at sea.
On one stone tablet that the admiral
later erected in Fujian, he describes
this great voyage.
We have traversed more than 100,000 lee
of immense water spaces and have beheld
in the ocean huge waves like mountains
rising sky high. And we have set eyes on
barbarian regions far away hidden in a
blue transparency of light vapors. While
our sails loftily unfurled like clouds
day and night, continued their course as
rapidly as a star traversing those
savage waves.
Although outfitted with cannons, the
treasure ships were not primarily
warships. They were in fact vast cargo
vessels. Their holds filled to the brim
with Chinese silks, cotton, tea, wine,
oil, iron, and candles along with other
luxuries. All intended for trade with
the strange lands they would encounter
along the way.
From these lands they brought back
spices, gemstones and even in the year
1414 a live giraffe which had been
brought to Bengal by some African
delegates from Malindi.
Impressed at the sight of the treasure
fleet, these men had gifted one of these
animals to the Chinese who brought it
home to no little amazement.
The Yonglur emperor was no stranger to
receiving exotic animals as gifts. And
there was even a part of his palace
devoted to keeping and caring for them.
Elephants and rhinoceroses from Champa,
bears from Siam, parrots and peacocks
from Java, and ostriches from Aiden.
But of all these, it was the giraffe
that he asked his court artists to
paint.
Alongside the vast treasure ships sailed
a countless array of different support
vessels, some carrying horses and
troops, others warships for defense.
Other boats were floating water tankers,
ensuring the thousands of personnel
wouldn't go thirsty on long voyages
between ports.
The ships communicated between one
another using large flags, signal bells,
a drum, and gongs
along with 10 lanterns that could signal
at night.
They even carried carrier pigeons to
communicate over longer distances.
The ultimate destination of the treasure
fleet was the city of Kolicode in the
modern Indian state of Kerala. But the
fleet was ordered to stop at every large
port and kingdom on the way to
demonstrate the might of the Ming
Emperor.
It was in 1406 that the Ming fleet
arrived in Java while the regreg civil
war was reaching its bloody height
when the Chinese treasure fleet arrived
in Java.
They might have expected to encounter
the scenes of wealth and prosperity that
had been recorded by previous visitors,
but they would find instead a troubled
land devastated by civil war. The
treasure ships anchored off the coast
and a group of Chinese soldiers and
merchants came ashore in western Java
hoping to trade.
But the western king Vikramina,
the husband of Haim Wuruk's daughter,
believed that his rival in the east had
brought the Chinese to intervene in the
civil war.
While the Chinese visitors were trading
in the marketplace, King Vikrama's
soldiers swept down on them from all
sides.
The cries of the Javanese warriors and
the screams of the dying would have
joined the pops and bangs of cannons
that would have sounded all around the
marketplace.
The acrid smell of gunpowder and blood
would have lingered on the air. When the
smoke cleared,
170 Chinese merchants and sailors were
dead, and the rest had fled back to
their ships.
Admiral Jungha had enough soldiers with
him that he could have invaded Java in
response. And perhaps like the Mongols
more than a 100red years earlier, he
could have decisively tipped the balance
in this civil war.
But he was a pragmatic man, and he
decided to tread a more considered path.
He treated his wounded on board the
ships and sent envoys back to the
Yonglur emperor asking him what to do.
In the time of Hayam Wuruk 30 years
earlier, China had steered clear of
conflict with the powerful Majapah
Empire, sending money and goods in order
to avoid a war. But now Majapah was
weakened and divided.
This time it was King Vikramma who would
send a graveling apology to the Chinese
court. And the Ming Shilu or Records of
the Ming dynasty records what the
emperor said in reply.
There is no doubt as to your guilt. You
acted on the basis of greed and anger
and you have acted against heaven. Is
there anything more serious than this?
Just as I was about to raise an army to
punish you, I have seen that you are
capable of repenting your mistakes, and
I have thus leniently stopped the
dispatch of troops. But what of the 170
people who died innocently?
You must immediately pay 60,000 leang of
gold as compensation for their lives and
to atone for your crime.
A year later, a Javanese ship arrived in
China with only a sixth of the sum of
gold that the Chinese emperor had
demanded along with a letter explaining
that the bankrupt kingdom could not
afford to pay anymore.
The Chinese emperor responded
magnanimously.
What I want from those people who live
far away is that they acknowledge their
guilt. But I do not want to enrich
myself with their gold.
The point had been made and the
humiliation of Majapah was total.
Everyone in the region took notice.
In 1424,
Chinese records show that when one king
in Sumatra died, his son sent out a
letter asking permission to succeed him
as king. And he sent it not to the kings
of Majapah in Java, but to the Chinese
emperor in the Ming court.
This shows just how far the star of
Majapahit had fallen and how the might
of China was on the rise.
Although Admiral Jungh had declined to
fight on this occasion, the treasure
fleet was more than capable of doing
battle on the seas. And alongside their
main diplomatic and merkantile mission,
its admiral had been given some less
peaceful tasks to complete on their
voyage.
Chief among these was a mission to
destroy the pirate fortress that still
held out at the Sumatran port of
Palumbang which had risen up due to the
weakness of the Majapahit Empire.
The Mingshi or history of Ming describes
how the pirate chief Chen Zooi had been
playing a clever double game, attempting
to mllify the Ming Emperor.
In the fourth year of the Yong Lay
reign, the pirate chieftain of the old
port, Chenhu Yi, sent his son to the
Ming court. However, although he sent
tributes to the court, he was plundering
the seas and thus obstructing the
comingings and goings of the tributes
envoys.
On its way home through the straits of
Malaca, the enormous treasure fleet took
its chance.
They sailed along the mangrove crusted
coast of Sumatra towards Palumbang which
the Chinese called the old port.
We can only imagine the site that
greeted the pirates of Palamang as the
hundreds of colorful ships bore down on
them on the horizon.
When they arrived at the port city, they
demanded the surrender of the pirate
chief Chen Zooi. According to the Ming
Shilu or records of the Ming dynasty,
the pirate chief attempted to use
deception to gain the upper hand.
When he arrived at the old port of
Palimang, he came across Ju Yi and
others and sent people to bring them to
negotiate their pacification. Juu Yi and
the others feigned surrender but
secretly plotted to attack the Imperial
army. Jeng Hur and the others found out
about this and marshalling the troops
prepared their defenses.
The ensuing battle would be the first
test of the power of the Yonglur
Emperor's fleet.
The Ming ships would have rammed into
the pirate vessels, hurled gunpowder
bombs from catapults, and fired special
kinds of fireworks filled with scraps of
paper designed to spread fire and terror
and ignite enemy sails.
They would have also sent volleys of
flaming arrows flying towards the pirate
ships.
The result was a resounding victory for
the Ming treasure fleet.
The pirate Jui suffered a great defeat.
Over 5,000 of the bandit gang were
killed while 10 of the bandit ships were
burnt and seven were captured. Further,
two counterfeit bronze seals were seized
and three prisoners, including Ju Yi,
were taken alive. When they arrived at
the capital in chains, it was ordered
that all of the prisoners were to be
beheaded.
With this pirate threat crushed, the
Ming Chinese quickly moved to establish
a governor of the area to prevent a
resurgence of any piracy.
The man they chose, a Muslim named Xi
Jinqing, had once been an official of
the Majapet Empire.
The old port pacification
superintendency was established and it
was ordered that Xi Jinqing be appointed
as the pacification superintendent.
A seal, a title patent, headwear and a
belt, patented fine silks and silk
gauses were conferred upon him.
While the rulers of Majapay had their
backs turned, fighting amongst
themselves, the Ming Chinese had swept
in and stamped their seal of authority
on the Malaca Strait.
To strengthen this grip over the narrow
and crucial waterway, the Chinese would
also bring under their wing the young
city of Malaca, which had recently been
growing in wealth and importance.
Malaca was a hub for another tide of
change that was now sweeping through the
archipelago.
That was the steady spread of the
religion of Islam.
Islam had long had a presence in the
Indonesian archipelago and had arrived
with traders who traveled back and forth
across the Indian Ocean, bringing nutmeg
and cloves to the markets of Egypt and
Arabia.
But now this young religion began to
make advances in all directions.
The European traveler Marco Polo
remarked on the change already underway
on the island of Sumatra when he passed
through the town of Perlac in 1292.
The people of Pearlac used to be
idoltors, but owing to contact with
Sariss merchants who continually resort
here in their ships, they have all been
converted to the law of Muhammad.
Part of the reason for the spread of
Islam on the archipelago was the
prestige and protection that the
religion brought.
One example of this in action is the
king Parameasara,
the ruler of Singapura, who had been
besieged by Majapahit under the reign of
Hayamuruk and had fled north to the
coast of the Malaka Strait.
There he had founded the city of Malaca.
And in order to add an heir of
legitimacy to his new rule, Paramasara
seems to have ditched his original Hindu
Buddhist name and adopted a new Persian
one, calling himself Sultan Iscander Sha
instead.
Muslim traders preferred where possible
to trade with other Muslims who were
more likely to share their languages of
Arabic or Persian, keep the same trading
and prayer hours, and shared a common
moral code. And so this connection
helped Malaca to rapidly expand.
The new city's strategic location, right
on the narrow sea corridor, meant the
Ming Chinese were also very interested
to bring its rulers under their
patronage and protection.
When Admiral Jung Hur arrived at the
port town of Malaka, he left a stone
tablet inscribed with a poem that
officially declared it under the
protection of China.
The vast southwestern sea reaches unto
the middle kingdom. Its waves cresting
high as the heavens, watering the earth
the same way for countless eons.
Washed by sunlight, bathed in the
moonlight, rain swept cracks and dewy
rocks in its midst luxuriate with
vegetation.
And in such a place, people live in
harmony. Its righteous king, paying his
respects to imperial power, wishes his
country to be treated as one of our
imperial domains and to follow the
Chinese way. So here, writ large on
everlasting stone, we do proclaim your
loyalty. Posterity will smile upon your
deed as time passes, and your sons and
grandsons will have limitless good
fortune.
In this, the Chinese were right. The
port town of Malaca would grow under
Ming protection to become the largest
and most important in the whole region.
When Jungh returned a few years later,
he would build a fort at Malaca to
protect it. And in return, the people of
the city would ensure that this crucial
waterway would be controlled by China
and China alone.
Wealth and trade that would have once
flowed through the ports of Java now
passed through the new trading hub of
Mala instead.
From this hub of commerce, the influence
of Islam would spread all across the
islands.
For the kings of Java who ruled
according to legitimacy derived from
their connection to the Buddha and the
god Shiva, each new convert reduced
their overall power.
Subsequent voyages by Jung Hur's
treasure fleets would sail as far west
as the straight of Hormuz, the city of
Mecca and Moadishu and Mombasa on the
East African coast.
But eventually the Ming would turn away
from oceangoing exploration.
When the adventurous Yong Lur emperor
died, he was replaced by more
inward-looking rulers who focused
instead on the construction of the Great
Wall in the north.
At one point, the Ming even outlawed the
construction of large ships, dismantling
some and perhaps even burning some
vessels in harbor.
But the decades when the vast treasure
fleets had sailed the seas left a
lasting impression on every culture that
they touched,
and the damage done to the image of
Javanese power was immense.
Eventually, the regreg civil war would
come to an end in Java and the western
king Vikramina Haim Wuruk's son-in-law
would be victorious.
Despite his humiliating and bankrupting
experience of angering the Chinese
emperor, he managed to close in on his
enemies in the eastern court. And in the
final bloody confrontation, the western
forces broke through the walls of the
eastern palace.
The lord of Fraabumi fled in the night
and escaped by boat.
He was hunted down and beheaded and his
severed head was brought back to the
capital of Majapahit.
The civil war was over and the kingdom
was united once more. But the conflict
had exacted a terrible cost.
In only 2 years of fighting, the
manpower of Majapahit had been severely
depleted. Its treasury was on the verge
of bankruptcy and its influence had been
drastically curtailed right at the point
when powerful rivals were rising in the
north and the religion of Islam was
spreading from port to port.
The center of the mandala of power had
now shifted irrevocably away from Java.
And the age of Majapahit's Empire of the
Islands would slowly but surely come to
an end.
While Majapahit lost much of its
overseas empire through the beginning of
the 15th century, it still remained the
preeeminent power on the island of Java.
But steadily, its loss of regional
status began to erode its power even in
its heartlands.
When King Vikram Vodina died in 1429,
his daughter Suittita took to the
throne.
She was prepared to rule in the
tradition of the great Javanese queens
who had preceded her a century earlier.
Diaragatry and Tribuano Vijaya
Tungadevi. But for a number of reasons,
her rule would be beset by problems.
Chief among these was a terrible famine
that descended on Java around the year
caused by a drought.
But the only source for this is the
chronicle of the Paraton
and by this point its reports are
becoming sparse and scarce and contain
little detail.
Next, there was a period of food
shortage that was very long in the year
of the serpents biting people.
Unfortunately for historians, the
decline of royal power in Java also
resulted in a disruption of the major
sources that we have relied on up to
this point.
Narrative texts like the paraton or book
of kings were crucial sources during the
golden age of Majapahit. But as we enter
the 15th century, the text becomes
increasingly obscure and difficult to
understand.
The chronicles notes get shorter
concerning only earthquakes and
eruptions and the deaths of kings and
they come further and further apart.
The final three pages of the Javanese
Book of Kings are just a few scraps of
seemingly unrelated information
separated by decades with its final note
coming in 1481.
Then a volcanic eruption occurred in the
wake of Watu Ganung in the Saka action
of the sky sea echore
perhaps in an attempt to alleviate the
effects of the drought. Suitta had
constructed a vast reservoir named Kolam
Seagaran just to the north of the city
of Majapahit.
This great pool was 800 m by 500 and
ringed all around by banks of red brick.
Whether or not this alleviated the
famine, we will never know. But it shows
the drastic situation that the empire
was facing around this time under
pressure from the environment, from
internal divisions, and increasingly
from powerful rivals.
When Suhita died in 1447,
her brother Ka Vagaya ruled for only
four years.
He was followed by a further four kings,
all of whom ruled for only a short time,
and the relationships between them are
unclear.
The kingdom erupted in civil war again
in the 1470s.
And in 1478,
one pretender broke through the defenses
of Majapahit and killed his brother who
sat on the throne.
That year in Java would be given a name
that seems to convey the mood in the
kingdom at the time. Sir Elanging Bumi,
which has been translated as vanished
and lost is the order of the world.
Upon his victory, this new king had
inscribed a series of stone inscriptions
that made dire warnings of the fate that
would befall any who failed to support
his rule.
They will end up in the realm of Yama,
the king of the dead.
They will be beaten by Yama's army for
years innumerable.
They will fall in the cauldron of hell.
They will not be reborn.
So, not only will they end up in hell,
but they will stay there. And even if
they are reborn, they will be reborn
under miserable circumstances.
It seems clear from these inscriptions
that the new king didn't feel at all
secure on the throne.
Throughout this period of political
instability, the situation for Majapay
would be made increasingly worse by the
rise of a new kind of power on the
coasts of Java.
That is the everinccreasing influence of
Muslim traders
with the powerful rival of Mal. Laka now
exerting its influence. Muslim merchants
had become wealthier and more
influential in Java than ever before.
And in the vacuum left by royal power,
these wealthy merchants became
politically powerful too.
Now more and more people on the coasts
all around the archipelago began to
flirt with the idea of this new
religion.
The Portuguese traveler Tom Perez
describes the steady advance of Islamic
power in Java at the expense of the
Hindu Buddhists who he calls heathens.
At the time when there were heathens
along the sea coast of Jaba, many
merchants used to come. Paris, Arabs,
Gujaratis, Bengales, Malaise and other
nationalities.
There being many Moors among them. They
began to trade in the country and to
grow rich.
They succeeded in way of making mosques
and mulas came from outside.
In some places the heathen Japanese
lords themselves turned muhamadan and
these merchant moors took possession of
these places.
The growing influence of these coastal
traders would culminate in 1475
with the foundation of a true Muslim
kingdom on the island of Java. A power
that would call itself the sultenate of
Denmark.
A port town looking north into the Java
Sea, Denmark had been founded in the
late 15th century, possibly by Chinese
merchants, and its people had built a
grand mosque there, combining elements
of Muslim and Javanese architecture.
The ruler of Damak was a man named Raden
Pata who was a vassel swearing
allegiance to Majapahit.
But he soon declared independence and
claimed the title of Sultan.
As Majapahed declined, the Sultanate of
Demach would expand.
It conquered the coastal region of Tuban
by 1527
and was spreading in land as far as
Malang by 1546.
For the dwindling power of Majapet, this
was the final death nail.
Due to the slow petering out of royal
chronicles in Java, we have few details
about what exactly happened to lead to
the eventual destruction of Majapahit.
But at this point, we are able to turn
to the writings of some outside visitors
to the island of Java.
Around 1513,
about 100 years after the end of the
Regreg War, the Portuguese traveler Tom
Perez visited Java.
He wrote in glowing terms about the
beauty of the landscape and the
abundance of the island. But he found
the power of Majapahit already a shadow
of its former glory. As he recounts in
his memoirs,
they say that the island of Jaba used to
rule as far as the spice islands on the
eastern side and over a great part of
the west. and that it had almost all the
islands of Somatra under its dominion
and all the islands known to the
Japanese
and that it had all this for a long time
passed until about a 100 years ago when
its power began to diminish and it came
to its present state.
Perez also alludes to some degree of
political instability in Java. According
to his account, the power of its kings
had diminished so that they were now
little more than a figurehead with the
Mahapati or prime minister appearing to
wield greater power.
Because the Japanese have lost a great
part of their lands, the kings do not
command, nor are they taken into
account, but only the viceroy and chief
captain. This man is known and honored
like the real king. All the lords of
Java obey him. Him they honor. This
governor commands in everything. He
holds the king of Java in his hands. He
orders him to be given food.
The king has no voice in anything, nor
is he of any importance.
Alongside this weakening of royal
authority came the fragmentation of the
kingdom.
Local lords became steadily more
powerful with some even breaking away.
And now the Muslim sultenates began to
taste blood in the water.
The sultan of the city of Demach, Raden
Pa, knew that only one thing stood
between him and ultimate power on the
island of Java.
That was the lingering remnants of
Majapahit.
After only a few years, he gathered his
forces and marched on the now isolated
city.
The later Muslim epic verse chronicle,
the Babad Tana Jawi, recounts what
happened next in heroic terms as the
Muslim forces bore down on the once
great capital city.
Then they agree to gather together all
Muslims with their arms. Then they set
out to Majapahed.
The number of troops was immeasurable.
The city of Majapahed was encircled.
Many inhabitants submitted to Raden Pa.
Nobody dared to meet him in battle.
Marching under blue and yellow banners,
they soon arrived at the walls of
Majapahit.
The later Muslim chronicles imitated
elements of previous Javanese legends
and claimed that the last king of
Majapahit was so aed at the sight of the
army approaching the city that he simply
ascended to heaven right there on the
spot and the city was captured
peacefully.
At the moment Prabhu Bra with Jaya
ascended to heaven, something like a
fireball was seen coming out of the
palace of Maja,
it flashed like a bolt of lightning and
sounded like a terrifying thunderclap.
It fell down in Binda.
Radan Pa entered the palace. He was
astonished that he did not encounter a
single person. He wept in his heart,
then left the palace and returned to
Bintara with his troops.
But we can assume that the end of
Majapahit was not as peaceful as these
later chronicers make out.
The historian Herald Vanderinda imagines
an extreme version of the scenes that
unfolded.
The soldiers met almost no resistance
and within an hour they had taken
control of the royal palace.
It was a massacre. Priests were drowned
in lotus ponds. Stable boys were stabbed
as they tried to protect the king's
horses.
Everything was burned to the ground. The
royal residences, the watchtower, the
pavilion with its intricate wood
carvings, the army barracks, the
elephant stalls, and the library.
By noon, all that was left of Maja Pahit
was a heap of rubble.
However, there is little evidence of
widespread burning at the site of the
city.
and no heaps of bodies or mass graves
have ever been found.
But what's clear is that at this point,
human habitation at the city of
Majapahit largely came to an end.
Its people fled and all of its houses
and workshops, its temples and palaces
were left to fade and crumble.
For many ordinary people, life simply
went on. But it must have been a time of
great upheaval and confusion.
The Javanese text, the Niti Shastra,
records one vision of the end of the
world that must have captured the mood
of many on the island of Java as their
world came to an end and another began.
The signs of the approaching end of this
world will be all kinds of depravity
among mankind. That is to say, the wise
will turn foolish. The holy men will
become worldly. Children will abandon
their parents. Princes will lose their
empires.
The little will become great and commit
depradations.
In short, everything will be in
confusion.
From this moment on, the Sultanate of
Demach would be the most powerful force
on the island of Java and the age of the
Hindu Buddhist kingdoms on the island
would come to an end.
Most remaining Hindus and Buddhists
would flee east and took refuge on the
small island of Bali which became a
sanctuary for their ancient culture.
Epic Hindu poems like the Bulman Taka
were largely forgotten on the mainland
of Java but in Bali they were preserved.
One verse in this poem describes the
destruction wrought by a demon king on
the religious sanctuaries of a kingdom.
And we might find it a fitting
description for the final days of Java's
last Hindu Buddhist sanctuaries.
Heaven is being destroyed and hermitage
is swept away because of the swarming
demons.
The hermits have left, have abandoned
all and fled far away, constantly
pursued
the miserable wretches.
Their bodies are lying about in the
monasteries with their bark clothing and
woven bags flung away.
With its people gone, the city of
Majapay would have been swiftly
reclaimed by the fast growing forest
around it.
The sophisticated drainage system that
its engineers had spent generations
perfecting that channels the slooes and
great reservoirs would have begun to
silt up within a decade without
maintenance. The water with nowhere left
to go would have pulled and spread,
turning streets into marshland and
marshland into swamp.
The red bricks that gave the ruins of
Majapahit its distinctive character were
fired from the volcanic clay of the Bras
River plane. And in the wet heat of
Java, they didn't last long.
Mosses would take hold first, then
lychans and ferns. The mortar softened
and dissolved. The strangler figs and
banyan trees would move in next,
clambering over the red brick courtyards
and ceremonial gateways of the Majapahit
capital. their roots clenching the walls
in their grasp and steadily but surely
pulverizing the brick.
Slower growing teak and mahogany trees
would arrive next, shading the crumbling
walls of Majapahit beneath their
canopies.
As all this went on, the great rumblings
of Java's volcanoes would have conspired
to hide the ruins even further.
More than 10 major eruptions of the
nearby Arjuno Wellerang and Anjas Moro
volcanoes took place in the centuries
that followed. Each one burying the site
of Majapahit in ever more ash until some
of its structures lay as much as 4 m
beneath the surface of the earth.
In the year 1849,
a Dutch traveler called Walter Robert
Van Hovl passed through the site of the
old city and described the overgrown
ruins that still remained.
The entire ruins were shrouded in a dark
forest and covered with shrs and trees.
Majestic Banyan trees have rooted their
roots between the stones and pushed
walls apart, raising their crowns high
above the ruins.
That is why nowadays the Javanese also
call the place Waning Lang or Banyan
Gate.
The Muslim sultenates that destroyed
Majapahit would not remain the most
powerful force in Java for long.
The next century would see the arrival
of other seaborn powers that would soon
form their ownthaloscracies
or empires of the sea.
These were the powers of European
colonialism.
In 1511, the port town of Malaka was
seized by the Portuguese and from there
their influence would spread all over
the archipelago.
Soon other European powers would arrive
and they would all begin to influence
the fracturous political life of the
island of Java and introduce the
beginnings of an ideology more seductive
and powerful than any religion, the
force of capitalism.
The Sultanates of Java would soon come
under the sway of a massive
international conglomerate and one of
the first joint stock companies in the
world, the Dutch East India Company.
In 1598, a Dutch fleet of eight ships
under Jacob Van Neck became the first
from the Netherlands to reach the spice
islands of Maluku.
In doing so, they bypassed the Javanese
merchants who had long dominated the
trade.
When these Dutch ships returned to
Europe in the year 1599,
laden with cloves, nutmeg, and mace, the
expedition yielded an enormous profit of
around 400%.
One Dutch observer would reportedly make
the following remark upon seeing the
arrival of this fleet.
As long as Holland has been Holland,
there have never arrived ships as richly
laden as these.
The age of European colonialism in
Southeast Asia had now begun.
Between6602
and 1796,
the Dutch East India Company dispatched
almost a million Europeans to Asia
aboard nearly 5,000 ships, dwarfing the
traffic of its nearest rival, the
British East India Company, returning
with more than 2.5 million tons of Asian
goods and enslaved people.
Throughout
this colonial period, which would
ultimately see Java become a European
colony, the legacy of the ancient
Javanese kingdoms was largely ignored or
intentionally obscured.
The Dutch in particular had no desire to
see the people of their new colonies
rally around the memory of any ancient
kingdoms and mostly declined to
investigate the ruins that could be
found dotted around Java.
The erasia was so extensive that in his
history of the Indian archipelago
published in 1820, the British writer
John Crawford was able to write the
following.
The theory of a great monarchy and of an
antecedent state of high civilization
and improvement has been forged by the
national vanity of the Javanese
unsupported by a shadow of proof and
contradicted by unquestionable internal
evidence.
But some memory of Majapahit's glory
lived on in the minds of Java's people
in their songs, their poetry, their
shadow puppet plays, and in the
manuscripts they kept in their
libraries.
In 1894,
in a typical expansion of European power
in East Asia, the Dutch colonialist
government intervened on the island of
Lombok to the west of Bali to depose its
king, a man named Aung Ketut Karangasam,
who was a renowned collector of ancient
texts.
After a protracted war in which the
local people resisted fiercely, the
Maharaja's palace was finally stormed by
Dutch marines on the 19th of November
1894.
The Dutch poured into the palace and
began a slaughter in which 2,000 were
massacred.
The Maharaja was captured and died a few
months later in a colonial prison.
During the fighting, Dutch artillery set
fire to the Maharaja's palace. And while
its towers burned and its roofs fell in,
the colonial troops looted the king's
treasury and carried away more than 130
kg of gold, 3,000 of silver, and
countless works of art.
This would become known as the Lombok
treasure.
But among the lutters there was also a
Dutchman named Yan Lawrence Andre
Brandes an expert in Sanskrit and old
Javanese.
This man had heard that the Maharaja
Karangasam was an avid scholar and a
collector of rare manuscripts.
As the Maharaja's palace burned, this
man ran to the ruler's library and saved
what he could.
While others ran with gold heaped in
their arms, Brandis frantically gathered
all of the ancient books he could carry
and fled before the roof of the palace
could collapse.
Much of the Maharaja's collection went
up in flames, and we will never be able
to read what was contained within it.
But what Brandes was able to save was
packed into a box and sent back to the
colonial capital.
Inside he would later find the only
existing copy of the poem the desavana
written by the self- aacing scribe
propanka some 500 years earlier.
In the pages of that work the voice of
the poet could once more bring to life
the description of its great king on his
journey around the island. the lives and
concerns of the people of medieval Java.
And at least in words, the kingdom of
Majapet could live once more.
I'd like to end this episode with an
extract from an old Javanese poem called
the Shiva Ratri Kalpa or the night
ritual of Shiva written during the years
of the decline of the Majapahit kingdom.
In this passage, a hunter named Lugdaka
stumbles upon the ruins of an ancient
temple and like Thomas Stamford Raffles
centuries later, would be struck by the
strange melancholy of these places where
once so many lives passed, now overgrown
with jungle.
As you listen, imagine how it would feel
to watch the palaces and temples of the
kingdom of Majapah crumbling into the
earth as its people left and its
reservoirs ran dry. Imagine wandering
beneath the shade of that teak forest
and watching the roots of banyan and
silk cotton trees slowly bind their way
over the ruins
as the layers of ash fell from the sky
season after season and covered the
works of man.
Imagine turning away and setting off
into the forest as the sun finally set
on Java's golden age.
A great temple complex from ancient
times rose near a mountain stream, and
the path there was lonely.
The curved trunks of the water elephants
had fallen and crumbled, and for lack of
care, its wall had almost tumbled down.
The monster heads seemed to be weeping
as their covered faces were overgrown
with creepers, and as though sad and
weary, the temple guardians lay rolled
over on the ground.
The pavilions in its courtyard were in
ruins.
Some of the buildings were now only
wreckage, while others were rotting
away. Their roofs were broken and had
fallen in, and beyond repair their
pillars stood a skew, swaying back and
forth.
Heartending was the spectacle of the
reliefs.
Young maidens in stone stood, gazing
skywards, full of sorrow, because now no
wandering poets ever came to visit them.
The tower temple soared on high and its
pinnacles served as a gathering place
for weeds. The sides were cracked,
overgrown by a shady fig tree which
spread luxurantly.
All the statues were cracked by a
fearsome tangle of vines, and only the
main deity within was immovably in
place, standing firm in the center of
its pedestal. Pandan trees hung down
over the rocks with an air of sadness
quite wrapped in the mist.
How they longed to be visited by the
thunder which would bring with it the
rushing of the rain.
As if in sorrow they let their petals
droop. Petals on which someone had
jotted down some words in a moment of
inspiration.
For is this not an admirable place for a
wandering poet to weave his verses.
Thank you once again for listening to
the Fall of Civilizations podcast.
I'd like to thank my voice actors for
this episode. Henry Stenhouse, Michael
Antonis, Alexandra Bolton, Simon
Jackson, Catherine James, Tom Marshall
Lee, Chris Harvey, Jack Jacobs, Nick
Denton, Amrit Sandu, Paul Cassell, Tim
Stevenson, and Amin Tahare.
Readings in old and middle Javanese were
performed by Feris Sanaya and Kada
Adita.
I'd also like to thank my historical
adviser for this episode Dr. Alex West.
Major sources used in the writing of
this episode were Majapahit by Harold
Vanerinda, the Indianized States of
Southeast Asia edited by Obalta F. Fella
and translated by Sue Brown Cohen. When
China ruled the seas by Louise Levaths
and New Insights on Majapahit, edited by
Henry Yogaspara and others. A full
public list of sources will be available
on Patreon linked in the description
below.
I love to hear your thoughts and
responses on social media, so please
come and tell me what you thought. You
can follow me on Blue Sky at
paulmcooper.com
and on Instagram at paulmcooper.
And if you'd like updates about the
podcast, announcements about new
episodes, as well as images, maps, and
reading suggestions, you can follow the
podcast on Blue Sky at
fallivilizations.com.
This podcast can only keep going with
the support of our generous subscribers
on Patreon. You keep me running. You
help me cover my costs and let me
dedicate more time to researching,
writing, recording, and editing to get
the episodes out to you faster and bring
as much life and detail to them as
possible. As a thank you, all
subscribers are able to listen and watch
video episodes completely adree.
If you enjoyed this episode, please
consider heading to patreon.com/fallof
civilizations_podcast
or just Google Fall Civilizations
Patreon. That's p a t r e o n.
for now. All the best and thanks for
listening.